<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Law-power, or, The law of relation written in the heart of ministers and people by the finger of God, is mighty through Him, to prevaile with both : to live as a people separated to their God, and from the world, specially at the Lord's Table.</title>
            <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66997</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25194</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08792780</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08792780</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41842</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66997)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41842)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1272:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Law-power, or, The law of relation written in the heart of ministers and people by the finger of God, is mighty through Him, to prevaile with both : to live as a people separated to their God, and from the world, specially at the Lord's Table.</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for Henry Cripps,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to H. Woodward--National union catalog pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41842:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41842:1"/>
            <p>LAW-POWER; <hi>OR</hi> The Law of Relation, Written in the heart of Miniſters and People by the finger of God, is mighty, through Him, to prevaile with both, to live as a people <hi>ſeparated</hi> to their God, and from the world, ſpecially at the LORDS TABLE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So ſhall we be</hi> ſeperate, <hi>I and Thy people, from all the people that are upon the face of the earth,</hi> Exod. 33. 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goe from the preſence of a fooliſh man, when thou perceiveſt not in him the lips of knowledge,</hi> Pro. 14. 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people, wherefore come out from among them, and be ye ſeperate,</hi> 2 Cor. 6. 16, 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come out of her My people, That ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues,</hi> Rev. 18. 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Henry Cripps</hi> in <hi>Popes-head-Alley.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41842:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41842:2"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF The ſeventh and laſt Treatiſe.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Six things are premiſed, which may help us to make judgement, whether the Miniſters of this perſwaſion, <q>
                     <hi>That all are to have Admittance to all Church-Communions upon account onely of their Infant Baptiſme,</hi>
                  </q> have the law of this Relation of a Miniſter written in the heart by the Spirit of God. Then is ſhewne, what this law of Relation is; And that where it is, and beareth rule in the heart of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and people, it will appeare ſo to doe, by what he teacheth his people, by his walke with them, and theirs with him, That all be well ſuiting to the Rule, decent, and according to Goſpel-order. In the next place is ſhewen, That the <hi>way</hi> of Gods people walking together according to Goſpel-order, is every where ſpoken againſt; And that <hi>Seperation</hi> from the world is the great <hi>offence</hi> in that holy way, yet ſuch a thing there is, and muſt be, a <hi>ſeperation</hi> ſutable to the mind of God; for he that will not <hi>ſeperate</hi> from the world, and falſe worſhip, is a <hi>ſeperate</hi> from God. There is a Communion of Saints on earth, they doe often meet and commune together. Some ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions anſwered, Miniſters that ſtand croſs to this way are adviſed; They that pretend to this <hi>way</hi> are Cautioned. The judgement of the learned and Godly is taken-in here, and ſo concluded.</p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>DEARE SIRS,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE crave leave to treat with you about thoſe words ere ſet downe in the cloſe of the former Treatiſe, <q>
                     <hi>The power and virtue of the law of Relation written in the heart;</hi>
                  </q> If ye never met with thoſe words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bleſſe God you have met with them, and make much of them now. Theſe are <q>
                     <hi>Maſchil,</hi>
                  </q> none like them ſo far as we know, to inſtruct your ſelves, and us to a right underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41842:3"/> of the way, to point the eye to it, to guide the foot in it, that our walke therein may be according to ſound judgement and diſcretion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>1</label> We have heard you ſpeake highly enough, and pray as earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Learned, and <hi>ordained</hi> Miniſters. Well, If you will ſay more, we thinke all the Godly in the land can joine with you in your deſires: but ſtopping there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we beleeve they will ſtop too, and cannot pray <hi>the ſame thing.</hi> Though yet we beleeve, That all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faithfull ſervants of Chriſt, have the <q>
                     <hi>mind of Chriſt,</hi>
                  </q> they love <hi>order,</hi> they hate <hi>confuſion.</hi> Notwithſtanding we take the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to tell you our perſwaſion <q>That a Godly man will aſſoone paſſe under <hi>Tyburne,</hi> as he will under the hands of thoſe Miniſters for <hi>ordination,</hi> whoſe way and judgement, as to Church-Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, is full-up with them ſo often mentioned.</q> And this be ſpoken without the leaſt refection of Diſhonour upon the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, governed by <hi>Presbyters,</hi> who ſeperate from the world at the Lords Table, as we ſuppoſe.</p>
               <p>Srs, We beſeech you for the Lord Jeſus Chriſt His ſake, and love of the Spirit; for His Churches ſake; for His Truths-ſake; for decencie, and order ſake; for the Office, or Stewardſhip-ſake, whereof you muſt give an account ſhortly, Conſider, putting it upon your thoughts: ye ſay ye are the Miniſters of Chriſt; ye ſtand in His ſtead; ye are Stewards in His Houſe, ye are Stars in His hand; What are ye not, which we, with your ſelves, account ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ourable, makes for your ſtabilitie, and ſtrength, ſecuritie, and ſafetie. Put this to your ſoules now; and if it be poſſible deale clearely and truly at this point in the reſolution of this Queſtion; <q>
                     <hi>Hath God cauſed you to paſſe under this Relation of Miniſters?</hi>
                  </q> Then He hath written the <hi>law of that Relation upon your hearts;</hi> What man hath done, ſhould be little with you, and without ſomething more, is nothing to us; Hath God cauſed you to paſſe under that Relation? that is the Queſtion: If you ſay yes, hold it forth, that all may <hi>ſee</hi> you ſpeake as well as <hi>heare</hi> you, and give Righteons judgement, <q>
                     <hi>That the Lord hath written the law of that Relation upon your hearts.</hi>
                  </q> Now the Lord God helpe you all, and every one to looke after this <hi>writeing of God</hi> upon your hearts; for we are more than jealous, as you give us ſad cauſe; That, it is not yet done, we meane the law of this Relation is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41842:3"/> not written upon your hearts. You may thinke it is, and you may ſay it is, It is nothing to us, nor we beleeve to any Godly man in all the whole Nation, what you ſay as to this matter, or what you thinke, while we ſee what you doe: <q>
                     <hi>Saul</hi> ſpeakes as confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, as you may doe, and ſurely he ſpake as he thought <hi>I have performed the Commandment of the Lord,</hi>
                  </q> which was, that<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Amalecke</hi> ſhould be utterly deſtroyed, nor perſon nor thing ſpared; <q>That you have not ſaid <hi>Samuell; What meaneth then this bleating of the Sheepe in my eares,</hi> and <hi>the lowing of the Oxen, which I heare?</hi>
                  </q> There are none ſo confident in beleeving (we meane a counterfeit beleefe) than are they, that are moſt outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious in ſinning; <q>
                     <hi>The foole rageth, and is confident.</hi>
                  </q> So may ye ſay ye <hi>have kept the charge of the Lord;</hi> You have performed His Commandment, ordering matters in His houſe, as becometh Stewards there.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>2</label> Firſt, This ye have not done ſure, for what meaneth thoſe abhominations committed there, not onely by your connivence winking at it, but by your allowance alſo, and more, your doing and juſtifying of what you doe, where it is done; what meaneth all this?</p>
               <p>Secondly, What meaneth then thoſe Beaſts in the ſhape of men, and they are the worſt Beaſts, preſenting their Infants to Baptiſme, and themſelves to the Lords Table? not requiring of them ſo much as a <hi>bare profeſſion of faith and repentance:</hi> all that, they can make; yet more than is required: What meaneth all this, <hi>if the law of your Relation be written on your hearts?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, What meaneth this (which being granted will proove an In<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let to, who knowes how great a flood of ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) That things muſt be ordered in Gods houſe, not according to the <hi>Principles grounded in Gods Word, but according to the Principles of Infant Baptiſme?</hi> What meaneth all this? <hi>If the law of your Relation be written in your hearts?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, What meaneth then, That unreaſonable, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men paſſe for <hi>Beleevers,</hi> having no faith; and for <hi>Diſciples,</hi> who hate Diſcipline; and for <hi>Saints,</hi> who perſecute holineſſe? If the <hi>law of your Relation be written in your hearts,</hi> can this be?</p>
               <p>Fifthly, What meaneth then, That this monſtrous body, we meane your Church, hath ſo much glorie, and favour in your
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41842:4"/> eyes; and the Church of Chriſt the true members thereof, as in charitie you ſhould judge, ſo little; That alone honourable with you, this alone deſpicable, ſo far as appeareth to mans eye; you are every day waſhing the face of the one to make it looke good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and faire before men, and ſo to <hi>in-ſtate</hi> it in, and <hi>poſſeſſe it of</hi> glorious matters, while you bewray the face of the other (which muſt needs be, while you waſh the one) not with <hi>duſt,</hi> as you may reade hereafter, but with <hi>mire,</hi> and <hi>dirt?</hi> Surely ye could not doe ſo, if the <hi>law of this Relation were writton on your hearts;</hi> for thus ye and we read; <q>
                     <hi>In whoſe eyes a vile perſon is contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; but he honoureth them that feare the Lord:</hi>
                  </q> Well, The Lord knowes who are His, and He hath made ſome of them to know it, that they are His, for Him they ſerve. And now they know, That He loves them, and <hi>to the end,</hi> that hath no end He loveth them. And now for mans love, if they have it they thanke him for it; if they have it not it matters little, and troubles them leſſe upon their owne ſcore. But this they know, That upon whoſe heart ſoever this <hi>law of Relation</hi> is written, this <hi>law of love</hi> is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten alſo; <q>
                     <hi>For every one that loveth Him That begat, loveth Him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> alſo that is begotten of Him,</hi>
                  </q> 1 Joh. 5. 1. <hi>Idem eſt motus animae ad finaginem &amp; rem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſome where; <q>The love that beares up the ſoule to God, beareth it alſo to the Image of God; <hi>Qui amat-ſupra amat infra,</hi> he that truely loves God above, heartily loves his Brothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> beneath.</q> But ſee what it is to ſwallow downe the Principles of Infant Baptiſme, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate all matters in the houſe of God according thereunto? as ſome doe; for it is to the men of that way and judgement we ſpeake.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, If you have the law of your Relation written upon your hearts; what meaneth then, that you doe with your poore people, <hi>ſottiſh,</hi> and <hi>brutiſh</hi> ones; ſo contrary to this law? In ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering them to take Sanctuary at the Ordinance of Baptiſme? thereby to ſhelter them from <hi>the wrath that is to come?</hi> and while they live in their ſinnes, give them right, and title to all Church-Adminiſtrations? Surely, ſurely, they, that feele the law of this Relation upon their hearts cannot doe ſo, no not for a world can they doe it; it were to make a poore ignorant people to <q>
                     <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve a lie,</hi>
                  </q> which we are aſſured is far from your purpoſe to doe:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41842:4"/> But you know there is <q>
                     <hi>finis operis,</hi> and <hi>operantis;</hi>
                  </q> utter deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſoules will be the <hi>end</hi> of this <hi>worke,</hi> though it is not <hi>your end</hi> that are the <hi>workmen;</hi> no, the thought of it, that you ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſoules is an abhomination to you. Let your worke, as to this matter, be an abhomination to you alſo. You cannot in evill things, and doiugs ſeperate the end from the meanes, (if the man will goe onn ſinning, his end will be periſhing for ever:) as ye ought not in good things to ſeperate the meanes from the end. (if the end I drive to, be eternall life, the meanes muſt be taken that conduce thereunto.) Therefore by the <hi>mercies of God,</hi> we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, and becauſe of the <hi>terrour of the Lord,</hi> His heavy wrath, and diſpleaſure, dolefull, and dreadfull puniſhments, that muſt be the portion of all <hi>Stewards,</hi> that feele not the law of their Relation written upon their hearts. by the finger of God there, and regard not to feele it, we would perſwade with you to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe matters, what your doings have been, and are, how agreeable to the mind of your God, rule of His word, law of your Relation; adviſe with one another about it, and then ſpeake your minds.</p>
               <p>Having praemiſed theſe ſix things for tryall, whether, the <hi>law of your Relation be written upon your heart,</hi> we proceed herein ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the propoſed Method, and firſt to ſhew</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat an influence this law of Relation written in the heart by the <hi>finger of God,</hi> hath upon the <q>
                     <hi>doctrine,</hi> and <hi>practiſe</hi>
                  </q> of a Miniſter; We will ſpeake of him ſingle; for as it is with one, it is with all, who find that <q>
                     <hi>law</hi> as aforeſaid, and of his <hi>Doctrine</hi>
                  </q> firſt,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>1</label> Firſt, He is his Lords <q>
                     <hi>Paranymph,</hi> or <hi>ſpokeſman,</hi>
                  </q> he ſpeakes a good word for Chriſt where ever he comes, if it be ſeaſonable, thereby to make-up the match, and <hi>betroth</hi> the ſoule unto Him; He laboureth to come within the boſome of a ſinner, and grapple ſo powerfully with his ſpirit, that He may take no nay at his hand: and for the attaining this end, and to make him ſee what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41842:5"/> need he hath of Chriſt; He will lay open the lothſome nature of ſin, and let-in the terrour of the Lord upon the Conſcience, that the careleſſe, and rebellious ſinner may come to a parley of peace, and be content to take Chriſt upon His owne tearmes, and take up the profeſſion of the Truth, and not ſtand at the <q>
                     <hi>Coſt</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">This is Gods reſolution to humble the ſoule ſo low till it can in truth and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs bid Chriſt wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come upon any conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. His mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and the blood of His Son is ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuable, that He will not caſt-it away where no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice ſhall be taken of it; but He will make the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt ſubſcribe experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally to that Truth of His. 1 Tim. 1. 15. <hi>D. Re. Tr: p.</hi> 389.</note>: Though ſo doeing he muſt part with all he hath of His owne, his deareſt luſt and all: And here He diſcovers to the ſinner, as he can, the cunning <hi>fetches</hi> of his curſed heart, and hunts him out of his <q>
                     <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi>
                  </q> that he may not cozen himſelfe, and ſit downe with ſome reſerved Deluſion, and goe no farther. And this is the Lords way ſure in <hi>whoſe ſtead</hi> he ſtands, and therefore craves of Him dayly <hi>His eye-ſalve,</hi> that he may <hi>ſtand in His counſell,</hi> and walke in His way, and doe that which he hath ſeene <hi>with his heavenly Father,</hi> as He hath done, and by His <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> ſtill doth; ſo doth he in His ſtrength, and by the directions of His Word; Wee will inſiſt upon this a little.</p>
               <p>When ever the Lord brings any ſoule over to Himſelfe, He firſt <q>
                     <hi>hideth pride from his eyes.</hi>
                  </q> Man, every man borne into the world, and growing up there, is a <hi>ſtout rebell,</hi> a <hi>ſtiffe-necked, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> as his father is; and as yeares adde Cubits to his ſtature, ſo is there an addition made to his pride, and rebellion: as he growes-up, he growes more like his father every day; now ſo ſoone as the Lord God is pleaſed to deale with this man by His Word, and Spirit, He knocks downe this <hi>Monſter pride,</hi> for this beares-up mightily againſt the Word, and Spirit, and, like the poſſeſſed man, breaks the <hi>cords,</hi> and <hi>bands,</hi> the good Spirit would binde him with; as eaſily till the Spirit hath ſet them on, as we can doe, <hi>burnt flax,</hi> or make a thred ſnap before the Candle. Therefore this <hi>prido</hi> is diſcerned, and ſlaine firſt, which is enmitie in the will, affections, and mind; There it is ſtill when diſcovered, and ſlaine there; but it doth a man no hurt, being diſcovered, and ſlaine, as pride doth not: for though it be, as they ſay, as the heart is, <hi>the firſt that lives, and the laſt that dyes,</hi> yet the man is hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for his pride, and walks <hi>ſoftly</hi> all his dayes, and doth put forth an holy enmity now againſt all that in his ſoule, which exalts it ſelfe againſt his God, his Lord, his Chriſt, and Word of His grace.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:41842:5"/>
               <p>Secondly, This is it he would bring home to his owne, and others hearts. The Lord God by His Word, and Spirit, <hi>hides pride from our eyes firſt,</hi> by giving us a ſight into our ſelves, what an <hi>hell</hi> there is within us, and makes it <hi>looke like hell,</hi> whereas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it might looke like <hi>heaven;</hi> what a <hi>dunghill</hi> there is within us, and makes us ſmell the ſtench of it as of a <hi>Dunghill,</hi> whereas before it did ſavour with us, as a garden of ſpices, or a bed of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; And then according to the exceeding riches of His grace, and abundant mercie through Chriſt, gives us a ſight of Himſelfe,<note place="margin">Job 42. 6.</note> a ſaving experimentall knowledge of Himſelfe in Chriſt; we <hi>heard</hi> of Him before with the hearing <hi>of the eare,</hi> (and how did we ſlight Him, till <hi>pride</hi> was hid from us, our proud heart was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued) but now <hi>our eye hath ſeene Him.</hi> And what then? Now He is exalted in our ſoules, for we are made low; Now He, and He alone riſeth in our thoughts higher, and higher ſtill, and ſo we fable; now <hi>ſin appeares to be ſin</hi> (the worſt can be ſaid of it) and grace appeares to be grace (the beſt can be ſaid of that too) <hi>it is grace;</hi> now Chriſt is exceeding welcome; for ſin is above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſinfull. He is pretious, ſin is vile.</p>
               <p>The <hi>hony-combe</hi> trampled upon before, while we were full of<note place="margin">Prov. 27. 7.</note> our ſelves, that is, <hi>proud,</hi> reliſheth now like an <q>
                     <hi>honey-combe,</hi> as it uſeth to doe with an <hi>hungry ſoule,</hi> and truely now we would <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre our ſelves, and repent in duſt and aſhes.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, To apply this to our purpoſe, ye muſt take Gods way, if you meane to doe Gods worke; and this way you cannot chooſe, but take when ever ye goe to worke, as <hi>workmen, that need not be aſhamed,</hi> feeling <hi>the law of their Relation written upon their hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Preach Chriſt unto the People, lift Him up as an <hi>Enſigne</hi> before them; So the Apoſtles did, ſo the Miniſters of Chriſt doe, that <hi>feele the law of their Relation;</hi> they tell their hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers what loſt ones they are <q>
                     <hi>without Him,</hi> what glorious crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures they are being <hi>found,</hi> and <hi>accepted in Him;</hi> His <hi>fullnes</hi> will convince us, as one ſaith, abundantly of our <hi>emptineſſe,</hi> His<note place="margin">Job 9. 148.</note> 
                     <hi>purity</hi> will ſhew us our <hi>ſpotts;</hi> His <hi>All ſufficiencie,</hi> our <hi>nothing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> labour by all meanes,</q> attend, and inſiſt upon the meanes, which you cannot, but doe, if you feele the law of your Relation, how to <hi>wooe</hi> for Chriſt, as His <hi>Paranymphs,</hi> ſpeaking a good word for Him.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41842:6"/>
               <p>Thirdly, Be ſure you lay your ground-worke well, we are more than jealous of you about that matter, as we told you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Tell your people home, as you can <hi>to their hearts,</hi> what a Cup of wrath they are borne to, and that they muſt drinke it up to the bottome, the very dregs of it, if they goe out of the world, as they came in, without any reall change wrought upon them by the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit;</hi> for they were borne Children of wrath, ſo ſoone as they were Children of men; and they have been ever ſince they were borne, filling-up <hi>their meaſures;</hi> and after <hi>their hardneſſe, and impenitent heart, treaſuring-up to themſelves wrath againſt the day of wrath, and the revelation of the righteous Judgement of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, And tell them herewithall, which you muſt needs doe, if ye know <hi>the law of your Relation, and feele it written upon your hearts;</hi> That their Church- priviledges they hold themſelves borne unto, being Baptized there, truſted to, and gloryed In, as <q rend="margQuotes">the manner is, ſtand them in no more ſtead, than the <hi>Arke at Shiloh</hi> did the Jewes, or <hi>ſacrifices</hi> multiplyed, or the <hi>Temple of the Lord;</hi> The <hi>Rocke</hi> and <hi>Manna; Circumciſion,</hi> or <hi>the Lords Super adminiſtred at Corinth;</hi>
                  </q> Beate them off from putting any Confidence in the fleſh; if you doe not, you doe nothing to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; nay you muſt tell them more, If no inward glory be gained by our glorious priviledges, (which indeed the Nation partakes off above many, if not above all in the world) theſe will ſerve but to expoſe us to more wrath, and fiery indignation from the Lord, rendring our condition worſe, than was theirs of <q>
                     <hi>Coraſin,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 10. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am. 4 6. 10. Ezek. 5. 10.</note> and <hi>Bethſaida,</hi>
                  </q> and our judgement from the Lord more <hi>intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable,</hi> even in this world, as <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> was, and at the end thereof, <hi>than Sodome's,</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah's</hi> was. And theſe things you will ſpeake before the people ſadly, and mournfully, as the Apoſtle ſaith; <q>
                     <hi>weeping;</hi> for you know who ſaid it, though you know he was an Heathen; <hi>If you will have us weepe, you muſt weepe firſt.</hi>
                  </q> When you find the <hi>law of your Relation</hi> preſſing upon your ſpirits, Ye will not mention before your people the <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Infant Baptiſme,</hi> as ye have <hi>gloſſed</hi> them with a <hi>Comment</hi> worſe than the text; nor will you make mention of god-fathers, or god-mothers either; Something we have read how they came in at firſt; But when the <hi>law of your Relation conſtraineth you,</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:41842:6"/> ye will ſee no need of them now, the <hi>Church of the living God</hi> ſhall be no more abuſed with them, nor that <hi>ordinance</hi> propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But theſe things yee <hi>know</hi> better, than we can tell you, <hi>Bleſſed are ye, if ye doe thereafter;</hi> And what are you if ye doe contrary to what you know? we ſay not, but leave it upon your thoughts.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Preach <hi>ſound doctrine</hi> to them, holding faſt <hi>the forme of ſound words;</hi> and whatſoever is contrary to it, Command them to <hi>bid defiance</hi> to it, yea to <hi>curſe</hi> it as <hi>Paul</hi> did, being that, which their ſoule muſt abhorre, when they feele the <hi>law of their Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> Thus ye doe, ye will ſay but we doubt it, becauſe your peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ſo well pleaſed with your doctrine; Now certaine it is, as once the Apoſtles found it to be, and told us it would ever be, eſpecially in theſe <hi>latter times, they will not <q>endure ſound doctrine,</q>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 3.</note> which will make them <hi>ſound in the ſaith.</hi> Sound doctrine is to a ſwiniſh ſpirit, (ſuch is every ſpirit by nature, till the good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hath wrought thereon,) like a corroding plaiſter to proud fleſh, or a launce to a ſore full of corruption, which will cut to the core, and cut it out. We intend cheifly this.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, While you are delivering forth unto them <q>
                     <hi>ſound doctrine,</hi>
                  </q> take this in with it, which ſhall argue its <hi>ſoundneſſe,</hi> and you <hi>ſound alſo;</hi> That your peoples hearts are very <hi>unſound,</hi> and their <hi>eares uncircumciſed,</hi> notwithſtanding with their eare they muſt attend, for therefore they have an eare, and the very <hi>male of their flocke</hi> they muſt lay out this way, all their ſtrength, elſe<note place="margin">Math. 1.</note> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>deceivers they are, and they are accurſed.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But this is not all you tell them, you will make them know, as ye can, That there is an <q>
                     <hi>intus prohibens,</hi>
                  </q> that ſtands within like an <hi>armed man,</hi> and till it be remooved, or ſubdued, will oppoſe all that is good, keepe it from entring the ſoule, viz: <q>
                     <hi>The enmities that are there againſt God, and the word of His grace.</hi>
                  </q> They come<note place="margin">James 1. 21. 1 Pet. 2. 1.</note> to heare, and caſt it out they cannot, nor is it poſſible with them, as their caſe is ſo to doe; yet are they commanded to doe it, nor is the command in vaine; They muſt endeavour to doe it, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to Him, and ſpreading it before Him, and attending the meanes whereby it is done, we meane, whereby this <q>
                     <hi>enmity</hi> (for that one word containes all) is diſcovered to us, and ſlaine in us by <hi>ſound doctrine ſoundly preached.</hi>
                  </q> This is the point you muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41842:7"/> upon, as did your Lord before you; <q>
                     <hi>The abſolute neceſſitie of regeneration, or of being begot and borne againe;</hi>
                  </q> doe not ſooth up your Diſciples with that vaine title, and lying vanitie, <q>
                     <hi>They were borne and baptized ſuch.</hi>
                  </q> It is notoriouſly falſe and knowne ſo to be in <hi>all the earth:</hi> We are borne more like <hi>Devills,</hi> than <hi>Saints;</hi> at the beſt, we beare the <hi>Image of the earthly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed you muſt tell them ſo, they are, while they are, as they were borne into the world, and beſt pleaſed to be what they are, ſo far from being <hi>Beleevers, Diſciples, Saints,</hi> that they are, as was ſaid, <hi>wolves, dogs, ſwine,</hi> and much worſe, becauſe a <q>
                     <hi>beaſt in the ſhape of a man is the worſt beaſt.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Ye have heard, or read what that excellent man Mr <hi>Bolton</hi> ſaid to his deare Children, when he was departing from them, <q rend="margQuotes">He verily beleeved that none of them durſt thinke to meet him at that great Tribunall in an unregenerate ſtate.</q> And was he not well aſſured of what he ſpake from his Lords owne mouth? <q>
                     <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh 3. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>a man be borne againe he cannot ſee the kingdome of God.</hi>
                  </q> And he gives the reaſon at the ſixth verſe, (we borrough that Learned<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>K.</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, <hi>pag</hi> 4.</note> mans words) <hi>for that which is borne of fleſh is fleſh,</hi> and is as <hi>unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſeeing the myſteries of the kingdome of God, as fleſhly eyes are of ſeeing Spirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ye muſt preach this <hi>ſound Doctrine</hi> to their eares <hi>ſoundly,</hi> and till it <hi>ſound</hi> unto their hearts, and is taking there, what ever they are in your eyes, they are as vile, as the vileſt in the Lords eyes, and in the eyes of His people, (for <hi>they are not waſhed from their <q>dung</q>
                  </hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 30. 12. Iſa. 4. 4.</note> and accordingly they muſt be dealt with, thruſt away from partaking in ſacred things, as you would heapes of dung out of the chiefeſt roomes. When ye are at this point dealing <q>
                     <hi>ſoundly</hi> with them,</q> ye will ſee cauſe to pray, and the godly with you, as the Primitive Saints for th' Apoſtles of Chriſt, <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Grant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 4. 29. 5. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>thy ſervants that with all boldneſſe they may ſpeake thy word, all the words of this life, that He commands you,</hi>
                  </q> for <hi>if all muſt be heard, all muſt be ſpoken,</hi> and ſpoken it muſt be, as the <hi>Oracles of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 10. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>God,</hi> and not teach onely, but <hi>command with all authority,</hi> that ſo ye may <hi>commend your ſelves to every man's conſcience in the ſight of God,</hi> as he did who felt the <q>
                     <hi>law of his Relation written in his heart;</hi>
                  </q> Your people ſhall know, if ye <hi>know the law of your Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> That ye are the Lord's Ambaſſadours, ye ſpeake in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41842:7"/> of Chriſt, and in the vertue of His Spirit, and muſt ſpeake as if <hi>Chriſt by you ſpake</hi> unto them, that is, as having <hi>power</hi> and <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> committed to you for the <hi>edification of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And be ſure ye begin right, Aſſuring them they were not borne with a Chriſt in their hearts, but enemies to Him; that they ſtand at an infinite diſtance from Him, and are wilfully ſet on it to have no acquaintance with Him; therefore they are but falſe conceits, and preſumptions, of their <hi>being in Him,</hi> before the Word, and Spirit hath been <hi>praevailing</hi> with them. Aſſure them, they, by nature, hate the Lard of life, and holineſs by Him, more than they hate that, their ſoule moſt loatheth; and they <q>
                     <hi>love</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 8. 36.</note> 
                     <hi>death,</hi>
                  </q> and a <hi>curſe</hi> in the procureing cauſe of it) as a father <hi>loveth his deareſt Child</hi> Theſe things ye muſt ſpeake to them <hi>with all boldneſſe,</hi> for theſe things are moſt profitable for them to know firſt. This our <q>
                     <hi>hurt is not to be healed with pleaſing words;</hi>
                  </q> But now ye ſhall be dealt hatefully with, dealing faithfully with them, as was told you, <q>
                     <hi>We cannot endure wholeſome words.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But the law of your Relation will helpe you to ſwallow that, and more; and ye can remember what the Lord, and Maſter found from His hearers, and all His faithfull ſervants ever ſince; This may comfort you too; you ſhall have no <hi>hurt</hi> from them, though they doe their worſt. And if you gaine any of them unto Chriſt, they will be your deare Friends to their death, becauſe <hi>you told them the truth.</hi> And for them that perſiſt in their hatred, you know it is not a <hi>ſimple hatred,</hi> with which we hate moſt hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full creatures; for it is <hi>mixed with feare, and dread of you,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them, as men that <hi>know the law of your Relation;</hi> they hate you, but they feare you too, <hi>as a man</hi> (ſo that learned man Dr <hi>Reynolds) <q>hateth a Lyon, or as a Malefactour hateth the Judge, as a theife hateth the light:</q>
                  </hi> For juſt reaſon we have been longer at this point; we leave it upon your thoughts, and ſo haſten to the <hi>practiſe</hi> of a Godly Miniſter, to ſee what that will be before his people, when he feeles <hi>the law of this Relation written upon his heart by the finger of God.</hi> But firſt we would for you and our Inſtruction, from theſe <hi>premiſſes</hi> draw theſe <hi>concluſions,</hi> and then, we will proceed to ſhew what a <hi>Godly Mans practiſe</hi> is, we meane, his, who feeles the <hi>law of his Relation written in his heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:41842:8"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>2</label> Firſt, That the ſame <hi>finger of God,</hi> which doth write the law of this Relation upon Miniſters hearts, ſheweth them the <hi>ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 16.</note> of their Lords houſe, how they ought to behave themſelves <q rend="margQuotes">there, all the <hi>formers</hi> thereof, and all the <hi>lawes</hi> thereof, writeth<note place="margin">Exek. 43. 11.</note> he in their ſight, as in former times ſo now that they may keepe the whole forme thereof, and all the ordinances thereof, and doe them;</q> But this the Spirit of God never doth before He hath made them <hi>aſhamed</hi> firſt of all they have done, contrary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the true way of Gods worſhip; They ſhall <q>
                     <hi>ſhame themſelves for this,</hi>
                  </q> or God will caſt ſhame upon them; He will humble them for all their abhominations before; He will reveale to them the <hi>right way of the ſervice of His houſe.</hi> And therefore it may be, God will not uſe thoſe Miniſters, how choice ſoever are their parts, who departed from God, when there was a generall depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Nation; for why may it not be now, as once God threatned; when <hi>Iſraell</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d depart from Him to falſe worſhip, <q>
                     <hi>That they ſhould beare their iniquities;</hi>
                  </q> they might be imployed in meane ſervices, but they ſhould not <hi>Come neare Him;</hi> The <hi>Lord had liſted up His hand againſt them;</hi> And it may be feared the Lord may doe ſo againſt ſome Miniſters, now adayes; How ever, except there be extraordinary repentance, and taking ſhame unto themſelves, The Lord may remember what they have done, <q>
                     <hi>when Iſraell departed from God:</hi>
                  </q> and what their complaints were, and what little uſe, and improovement they have made of the <hi>bleſſed liberties</hi> they have had ſince to order matters in their Lords houſe full-up to what He hath commanded. In the next place</p>
               <p>Secondly, They that know whoſe <hi>ſpokesmen</hi> they are, in whoſe ſtead they ſtand, have <hi>learnt Chriſt,</hi> and can <hi>teach Him, uſeing great boldnes, and liberty of ſpeech;</hi> They are as the <hi>Officers of a great Prince</hi> going before Him, to praepare a way for Him, and will make bold to ſtrike and to ſcatter thoſe unruly throngs of men, who preſſe too neare upon His ſacred preſon; They will boldly ſmite with the <hi>rod of His mouth;</hi> they will cry aloude, and not ſpare; they will (as he ſaith) pull downe <hi>mountainous luſts, ſubdue ſtrong holds;</hi> They will, in the ſtrength of God (that is the ſcope, and end of their Miniſtery) bring low every <hi>mountaine, and hill;</hi> make the <hi>crooked ſtraight,</hi> and the <hi>rough ſmooth;</hi> This in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41842:8"/> deſire and endeavour they doe. And if any ſhew themſelves ſtout againſt againſt God, making their <hi>browes braſſe;</hi> Theſe will ſet their <hi>faces as flint</hi> againſt all theſe; for ſo God hath commanded, and ſo doth the law of their Relation command</p>
               <p>Thirdly, They doe all things in right order, and according to their patterne: they proclaime <hi>war</hi> firſt with mens luſts, come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as with a <hi>ſword</hi> in their hand, and <hi>fire</hi> in their mouth againſt them, and ſo make <hi>roome for peace</hi> in the hearts of men, <hi>which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all underſtanding;</hi> But they will make them know firſt they are enemies to <q>
                     <hi>this peace,</hi>
                  </q> while they are enemies to <q>
                     <hi>holineſſe,</hi>
                  </q> and friend with themſelves, and their ſins. Theſe that underſtand their <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> the <hi>power of Chriſt</hi> they are inveſted with, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the <hi>law of their Relation,</hi> will aſſure them, that they muſt <hi>caſt hell</hi> upon their <hi>ſins,</hi> or upon their <hi>ſoules;</hi> If they will continue to be workers of iniquitie, they will hold-on to worke out their damnation to the utmoſt.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, They that preach as men that know the law of their Relation, find not one <hi>principle</hi> (of <hi>holineſſe</hi>) no not one, thorough the whole booke of God, which is <q>
                     <hi>peaceable.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed all tends <hi>to peace at laſt,</hi> but intends <hi>warre at firſt.</hi> What may be found among the principles of Infant Baptiſme, they know not, nor will they ſeeke to know; They will goe by Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule, which aſſureth them, if they <hi>pleaſe men</hi> (mens luſts) they <hi>cannot pleaſe God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, Theſe ſearching, and reprooveing Miniſters, theſe profit the hearers, and doe their ſoules good; theſe, and onely theſe; whereas a partiall, unſearching, and un-reprooveing <q rend="margQuotes">Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter (to uſe that learned mans words) is one of Gods curſes againſt a place, the forerunner of a finall, and fearefull viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;<note place="margin">Hoſ. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> The dayes of viſitation, and recompence come ſaith the Lord; the Prophet is a foole, the ſpirituall man is mad; for the multitude of iniquitie, and the great hatred. If a man,<note place="margin">Mich. 2. 11.</note> walking in the Spirit, and falſhood, that is, profeſſing the worke of a ſpirituall man, and yet betraying His Office, or in a falſe, and lying Spirit prophecying of <hi>wine, and ſtrong drinke,</hi> that is, cheriſhing and encourageing ſenſuall Livers in their pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous courſes; <hi>He ſhall even be the Prophet of this people.</hi>
                  </q> Thus in all ages, and never more apparently thus, than now in our dayes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41842:9"/> hath the Lord puniſhed with an extreame revenge the Rebellion of a people againſt His Goſpell.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, They that will preach the Truth as it is in Jeſus, as their love of Chriſt, and law of their Relation conſtraineth them, ſhall find <hi>Luthers</hi> words true, <q rend="margQuotes">That this preaching will derive the hatred of the world againſt them.</q> They ſhall ſtand as a Marke for all the world, with the <hi>god</hi> thereof, to ſhute againſt. Therefore, (for ſomething hath been ſpoken this way already, and more may be ſpoken anon.) In the laſt place.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Theſe are, and there is more than need they ſhould be ſo <q>
                     <hi>above the world;</hi>
                  </q> They are <hi>dwellers in heaven;</hi> Chriſt in them by His Spirit, they in Him by their faith; they feele the <hi>law</hi> of their <hi>Relation</hi> working as ſtrongly in them, as the <hi>law of ſin</hi> in their enemies; and ſo they can, as was ſaid of <hi>Luther,</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>beare the hatred, and ſhocke, the rage and violence of the whole world;</hi>
                  </q> they have a backe of ſteele, and underneath <hi>everlaſting Armes;</hi> they cannot be greatly mooved, never remooved from their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor-hold. We proceed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§. </seg>3</label> The law of the Relation written upon a Miniſters heart, is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailouſly prevailing to regulate his <hi>practiſe</hi> before his people, and within Gods houſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, His practice will be humble, and meeke; ſo he will walke with his God, and before His people. The Godly wiſe<note place="margin">A lifted-up ſpirit (in any man) the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt cloſer of the heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth of God. Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> of <hi>Jol.</hi> 72.</note> will never thinke him to be a man of God, if he be proud, and haughtie. It was a diſtinguiſhing Character, that <hi>Beda</hi> gives, whereby to know a man of God, and that he will preach to the people the preaching of God: <q rend="margQuotes">If he be a man of God follow him, ſaith he of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that counterfeit Saint, And <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> faigned Apoſtle. But how ſhall we know, ſaid the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whether he be a man of God, or no? <hi>Beda</hi> anſwered; If he be gentle, and lowly of heart, he carryeth the yoake of the Lord, and will offer unto you to carry the ſame yoake; but if he be diſdainfull, and proud, then it is certaine, he is not of God, nor hath heard Gods word, nor can endure His yoake, and little good ſervice can he doe; <hi>A proud perſon being like a gouty hand, or ſwelled Arme, which troubleth the body, doth it no ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:41842:9"/>
               <p>Surely a true ſervant of Chriſt is as like his Lord and Maſter as can be, <hi>lowly, and <q>meeke;</q>
                  </hi> for he remembers ſtill, that for His ſake, and to teach him, He ſtooped as low, as <hi>the feete, and waſhed them;</hi> and a little while after became a <hi>Worme and no Man, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Himſelfe, and became obedient unto the death, even the Death of the Croſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, As he feeles the <hi>law of that Relation,</hi> of a Miniſter, ſo alſo, of a <hi>father</hi> to His people, and they to Him in the Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Children, even as <hi>Paul</hi> was, he deſires, and endeavours to be <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>gentle among them, as a nurſe,</hi> cheriſhing her children;<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>exhorting, comforting, charging every one, as a father doth his children;</hi>
                  </q> And how <hi>curiouſly</hi> doth he walke before them, looking round about him, leaſt he ſhould looſe his way, or miſſe his end,<note place="margin">Eph. 5. 15.</note> and ſhould be blamed in that, for which he blames others; he conſiders with all his heart, <hi>turpe eſt Doctori,</hi> And remembers all along his walke, that his people obſerve him more in the ſtreete, within, or without the houſe, than they doe in the pulpitt; their eyes are more intent upon his <q>
                     <hi>doings;</hi> than their eares are unto his <hi>ſayings;</hi>
                  </q> and thereafter they faſhion themſelves, and their whole courſe commonly, by what they ſee him doe, not to what they heare him ſay, unleſſe he ſpeakes to pleaſe their Luſts; Therefore feeling this <hi>Law of his Relation,</hi> with all his care, he is carefull here; ſo as he can ſay, as his patterne before him; <q>
                     <hi>Yee are witneſſes, and God alſo how holily, and juſtly, and unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably We behaved our ſelves among you that beleeve;</hi>
                  </q> (And they were as carefull to give no offence to them that were without) We muſt adde this, That there be no miſtake here. Theſe that know the law of their Relation, behaving themſelves thus <hi>gently,</hi> are as ſharpe as who are ſharpeſt, in reprooveing of ſin, for it is good to reproove, as God reprooves. Ye remember who he was, that did not <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>frowne</hi> upon ſinners becauſe they were his ſonnes; but God <hi>frowned</hi> upon him, and brought ſore diſpleaſure upon his family: Great ſinners muſt have great reproofes; as he ſaith;<note place="margin">Job 13. 39<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</note> Some muſt be <hi>ſaved by feare,</hi> a ſanctified meanes to pull them out of the fire. Ye muſt caſt them into the fire, that they may eſcape the fire; <hi>Pittifull cruelty is better than cruell pitty.</hi> Some in dealing both with ſinfull practiſes, and erroneous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of men, handle them, as men handle thornes, as if they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41842:10"/> durſt not touch them; <hi>this fatneth ſin, and confirmeth errour.</hi>
                  </q> May we not adde; doe not ſome deale with Drunkards, as ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as they ſhould deale with Diſciples? And with notorious ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners (unexcommunicate) as if they were Saints? It were infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly better for them, if they had been <hi>delivered-up to Satan;</hi> for now they are delivered-up to their owne hearts luſts. <q>
                     <hi>Lyars, evill Beaſts, Slow-bellies,</hi> (as the moſt of your Nominall Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers are, if not all) muſt be rebuked <hi>cuttingly,</hi>
                  </q> that they may <hi>be ſound in the faith. Sores muſt be cut, and lanced, before they be healed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, They that know the law of their Relation, and feele it upon their hearts, doe know, they ſtand before the people as Ambaſſadors ſent unto them from <hi>the Prince of the Kings of the earth;</hi> nay they are in <q>
                     <hi>Chriſts ſtead;</hi>
                  </q> therefore as they muſt ſpeake unto them, whereof before; ſo muſt they deale with them, as to all Church-Adminiſtrations; neither more nor leſſe; but full-up to their <hi>Commiſſion;</hi> even as Chriſt Himſelfe did doe, when He was upon the Earth, and hath appointed to be done, till His returne from Heaven, all that, which is comely to be done, by all thoſe, that <hi>ſtand in His ſtead;</hi> and <hi>are Stewards in His houſe;</hi> whereto ſo much hath been ſaid, that we ſhall ſay no more to it in this place; Nor ſhall we ſpeake to this Relation, which indeed containes much: they ſtand in <hi>Relation of Shepheards</hi> to their ſheepe; they walke-on before them (like the <hi>Admirall Ship</hi> carrying the <hi>Light</hi>) and they looke well to their walke, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve as well, who followes them; and accordingly they deale with them; and who will not follow them, but follow <q>
                     <hi>after Srangers,</hi>
                  </q> unto Strangers let them goe; for theſe good Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards will make a difference, as becometh men inſtructed to<note place="margin">Ezek. 34. 17.</note> Diſcretion: and ſo are enabled to judge between <hi>Cattle, and Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> the <hi>Rams,</hi> and the <hi>He-Goates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When we have ſaid all, (and how little is our All in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters?) ye may ſumme-up all in this one <q>
                     <hi>Relation</hi> of a <hi>Miniſter of Chriſt;</hi>
                  </q> he that finds the <hi>law of that one Relation</hi> written in his ſoule by the finger of God, they humble themſelves to walke with their God; and treate with their people, as a father with his children; ſtanding before them <hi>in Gods ſtead,</hi> they deale with them, as becometh faithfull <hi>Stewards,</hi> and good <hi>Shepheards.</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:41842:10"/> In a word, They make cleare proofe, that they have learnt Chriſt, and can teach him; when they <hi>ſhew forth His life in theirs;</hi> when they <hi>walke, even as He hath walked;</hi> when, <hi>as <q>He was, ſo they are in this world;</q>
                  </hi> when the ſame minde, judgement, affections are in them, which were in Chriſt Jeſus their Lord.</p>
               <p>From all this, we would draw theſe Concluſions, and then proceed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>4</label> This Miniſter of Chriſt, that feeles the law of his Relation written upon his ſoule, fully knowes, <q>
                     <hi>Intus &amp; in cute</hi> as ye ſay,</q> or endeavours his utmoſt ſo to know, <hi>the ſtate of his people,</hi> as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly well in deſire, and endeavour, as a <hi>father</hi> doth the ſtate of his children; a <hi>Steward</hi> the ſtate of the houſehold; the <hi>Shepheard</hi> the ſtate of his flocke. It is his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and not a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, his very worke, and buiſines to <q>
                     <hi>know That;</hi> we meane the ſtate of his people; for,</q>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Put the caſe, (for teaching ſake we may doe it, though it be not poſſible, but that a Miniſter knowing that Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt know it) That <hi>he knowes not the ſtate of his people;</hi> then this muſt follow; he muſt ſpeake unto them <hi>generalls</hi> onely, for not knowing their ſtates in particular, he cannot ſpeak unto them in particular, and ſo deale with them anſwerably. Some of them <hi>declare their ſin as Sodome, they hide it not:</hi> they trample <hi>pearles</hi> under their feete, turne againe and rent the Diſpenſers of them; accordingly theſe muſt be dealt with. Some againe, and none of the worſt have need of <q>
                     <hi>Corroſives;</hi>
                  </q> other ſome may need <hi>Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als;</hi> Some have need to be <hi>ſearched,</hi> and <hi>humbled;</hi> ſome to be <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged,</hi> and <hi>comforted;</hi> their ſtates in particular muſt be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into, that the Miniſter of Chriſt may doe accordingly. We remember the expreſſion, that <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Confeſſe your faults one to another,</hi> and <hi>pray one for another, that ye may be healed.</hi>
                  </q> As if he ſhould ſay, none can be able to pray for you ſo effectually for your comfort, as thoſe, That know your ſins well, and ſo can confeſſe them before God. <hi>A Miniſter muſt know the ſtate of his flocke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, That there is no caſe, or condition, theſe people can be ſuppoſed to be in, but this Miniſter of Chriſt upon whoſe heart the <hi>law of his Relation</hi> is written, is able in the ſtrength of Chriſt, by the ſupply of the Spirit, to give in that, which ſhall fitt the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41842:11"/> caſe, be an adequate, or proportionate helpe, ayde, ſuccour, cure thereunto; he ſhall be able to give-in <hi>Reproofe, correction, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, counſell, comfort,</hi> as the caſe and condition ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. And</p>
               <p>Fourthly, In the laſt place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This will follow: If their eſtates in particular muſt be enquired-into, then they muſt be dealt with in particular, alone, and apart; And there muſt be time and place for it. This the people will not endure, and this courſe ye ſeeme not to approove, neither, we ſhall heare your reaſons, wherefore, in due place. We have told you what you will teach in point of Doctrine, and what you will doe in point of practiſe, ſo ſoone as ye ſhall feele the finger of God writing the <hi>law of your Relation</hi> upon your hearts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>1</label> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow we proceed to tell our ſelves, and you, if ye will heare what thoſe <hi>people</hi> will doe, in whoſe hearts the finger of God hath written the law of their Relations. They will ſpeake, and doe the very ſame thing, which all Gods people, Miniſter and people ſpeake, and doe, in whoſe hearts the Law of their Relation is written.</p>
               <p>It may be asked here; What are theſe Relations? And what is the Law thereof? Breifly, and to narrow theſe matters as much as we can.</p>
               <p>Their Relations are theſe; Firſt, The great, and dreadfull God for His deare Son's ſake (manifeſted in the fleſh) ſtands related to them, as theirs, <q>
                     <hi>their God;</hi>
                  </q> they to Him, as <hi>His people;</hi> more particularly, the great God ſaith of every one of theſe; <q>
                     <hi>Thou art my Diſciple,</hi> thou <hi>art mine,</hi>
                  </q> Iſa. 43. 1. He againe Ecchoeth forth to his God, <q>
                     <hi>And I am thine Lord;</hi>
                  </q> (for all is recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call between God, and this gratious Saint). The intercourſe is mutuall; if He ſay, He is ours; We ſay againe, we are thine Lord, and we give our ſelves to thee; <hi>The claime is mutuall;</hi> He claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us for His; we Him, for Ours. <q>
                     <hi>Thou art mine; I am thine.</hi>
                  </q> Breifly, there is the Relation; Now the Law is this; As Jehovah God ſaith to this perſon (ſo ſingly we muſt ſpeake) All I am, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41842:11"/> I am all; All I have, and I have all; All I can, and I can all, I am for Thee, who doeſt truſt Me, art my <hi>Diſciple indeed,</hi> My <hi>Saint</hi> in <hi>Truth;</hi> So now ſaith this Beleever, this Gracious Saint, this <hi>ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated-one,</hi> What I am, it is of Thee; What I have, it is from Thee; What I can, it is by Thee. All I am, I have, I can, it is <hi>for Thee O my Beloved</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Cant. 7. 13.</note>; It is a Curſe that one ſhould ſowe, and another reape; It is God that ſowes, ſhall the fleſh, or the world, or the Devill reape? God forbid, He that ſowes, He ſhall reape, ſaith that perſon, that feeles the Law of His Relation. For thus this Perſon ſaith to his <q>Lord, and his God. Thou haſt ſaid, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it pleaſed Thee, ſo to ſay, That all <hi>Thine is mine;</hi> And by Thy grace, I ſay, and ſhall never ceaſe ſaying of it; <hi>And All Mine is Thine.</hi>
                  </q> There is the Law of that Relation.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The great God ſtands to them in the Relation of a <hi>Deare Father;</hi> they to Him as <hi>Deare Children;</hi> God ſaith to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them firſt, or laſt, I am thy Father, and call Me ſo, <q>
                     <hi>My Father;</hi>
                  </q> He, or ſhe Ecchoes againe to Him, <hi>Thy ſonne, Thy daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> there is the Relation; The law thereof is this; This Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father in, and through Chriſt, makes over Himſelfe unto His Childe; <q>
                     <hi>His Love and all;</hi>
                  </q> This Child makes a deed of gift, as we may ſay, of himſelfe backe againe, unto his Father, through Chriſt, by Whom he received all, gives Him all his <hi>love,</hi> and all too little (yet he has not the leſſe, but much more for all his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations here below, well corrected, and ordered, now God hath all) all <q>
                     <hi>his love,</hi> and all <hi>his feare,</hi> and all <hi>his ſervice</hi> (but <hi>feare is all</hi>)</q> And now this Child <hi>ſhall be ſpared,</hi> as a <hi>father ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his, and ſo he ſhall be ſerved,</hi> For all things in heaven and earth ſhall ſerve him, and Miniſter to him, if need be; And this Child, while he is himſelfe, and not over-taken nor ſurprized, is as tender of his Fathers Name, as he is of that he moſt dearly loveth, and as fearefull to offend Him, as he is to offend the tendereſt part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, the apple of his eye; There is the great Law of that Relation alſo.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The great God ſtands to them in Chriſt, as a <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome</hi> (for as was ſaid, His love never decayeth; as ſervent at laſt, as at firſt) they to Him, as <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>His Spouſe;</hi> He ſaith to every one of theſe firſt, or laſt, I am <hi>marryed to thee;</hi> Thou art my <hi>Hephzi-bad,</hi> my <hi>delight is in thee; I am for Thee;</hi> and <hi>Thou
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41842:12"/> ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> not be for another,</hi> Hoſ. 3. 3.</q> There is the Relation: The Law is this: The <hi>Bridegroome is intirely the Brides;</hi> The <hi>Bride is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely the Bridegroomes.</hi> His <hi>delight is in her</hi> (that implyes all, tongue can expreſſe, or heart can wiſh open it never ſo wide) <q>
                     <hi>her delight is in Him,</hi> and that implyes alſo all that is expected from her: He ſits downe with <hi>great delight</hi> taking pleaſure in her;</q> and ſhe with the ſame delight, in her meaſure, taking <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in Him.</hi> There is the <hi>Law of that Relation;</hi> we might be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry large, and it is hard to ſpeake little of ſo much as might be ſaid, once more.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, He ſtands to them, as a <hi>Lord,</hi> they to Him as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; He ſaith to every one of them, <hi>Thou art my ſervant:</hi> he, or ſhe to Him againe; Thou art my <hi>Lord,</hi> (a Name of as much uſe and comfort as Jeſus is with a Saint) and <hi>my God:</hi> There is the <hi>Relation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <q>
                     <hi>Law</hi> is this, <hi>Thou ſhalt doe all that I command thee,</hi>
                  </q> as to the ſubſtance, or matter, forme, or manner of the worke; what I command thee, and as Ile have it done; <hi>all My will,</hi> and, <hi>all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to My will.</hi> The <hi>matter</hi> of a ſervice hath been rewarded, when the <hi>manner</hi> of doing it hath been revenged. I doe it, Lord, ſaith this <q>
                     <hi>ſervant;</hi> ſpeake, Lord, thy ſervant heareth; Command, Lord, thy ſervant doth it;</q> 
                  <hi>As the eyes of a ſervant lookes to the hand of his Maſter; as the eyes of a Maiden to the hand of her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, ſo my eyes waite upon Thee, my Lord, and my God.</hi> We will onely name two Relations more.</p>
               <p>The Great God ſtands related to theſe His people every one of them, as a <hi>friend</hi> to a <hi>friend,</hi> as a <hi>Shepheard</hi> to his flock. From this, and all that which went before, we will ſet downe theſe Conſectories.</p>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, Theſe are a peculiar, and choice people, a royall Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, of whom God ſaith, <q>
                        <hi>You are my people;</hi>
                     </q> They againe, <hi>Thou art our God;</hi> and being ſuch they muſt accordingly be dealt with. <q>
                        <hi>They ſhall dwell alone, they ſhall not be numbred among the Nations.</hi>
                     </q> There ſhall be a better account had of them, who can give a <hi>reaſon of their hope,</hi> than is of your Diſciples, Beleevers, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41842:12"/> Saints; of no more account with their God than <hi>Infidels</hi> are, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos</hi> 9. 7. While they can give no other reaſon of their hope, but that they were borne and baptized in the Nation.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, They are Children<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and every one expects a Childs portion; Childrens bread to be given unto them, and they will not receive it among the Dogs; They are <q>
                        <hi>marvailouſly ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi>
                     </q>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 4. We muſt be ſeparated from them here, or in hell live with them for ever. Learned, and Holy <hi>Sibs.</hi>
                     </note> and now they can no more mixe themſelves with the wicked, "<hi>workers of iniquity</hi> (though they would ſtoope to their foote; or take them into their beſome to doe them good) than they can <hi>mixe with their workes;</hi> or <hi>light mixe with darkneſſe,</hi> or <hi>Christ with Belial.</hi> The Children of God, they will not at any time, or place, unleſſe by a good warrant, much leſſe at the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, mixe with the Children of the Dev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll, their deareſt fathers enemies as well as theirs.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, They are the <hi>Spouſe of Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>His Bride;</hi> They will, through grace, carry themſelves honourably, and as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the <hi>Law of that Relation.</hi> And if ever you will deale with them, which you will doe, if you know the Law of your Relation, you muſt take them out of the throng and tumult of the world, as was ſaid; <q>
                        <hi>The Bride of Chriſt is a virgin modeſt and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt;</hi>
                     </q> you <hi>muſt appoint a ſet time and place to meete with them.</hi> If ye will not doe ſo, not <hi>feeling the law of your Relation upon your hearts,</hi> they will meete without you, and they know who will give them a meeting (they doing all they doe decently, and in order) He, Who never failed them hitherto; You muſt take them out of the throng, and tumult of the world alone, and apart, as the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved His Spouſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 7. 11. and as He tooke the blind man out of the Towne, <hi>Mark.</hi> 8. 23. And</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Theſe are the ſervants of the moſt High God; And the Law of that Relation gives Law to their thoughts, all their ſaying and doings. Their eyes looke up to their Lord, what He Commands that doe they, and what He forbids that they avoide as an <hi>Adder</hi> in their path, or <hi>a ſhe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Beare</hi> in their way: What care they what the <hi>principles of Inſant Baptiſme</hi> ſay, if theſe ſay but accoring to that, we have heard ſayd; they heare what the <hi>Word</hi> ſaith, for the word hath <hi>bored their eare.</hi> They follow their Lord going before them by His Spirit in the directions of His word, for they <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>know His voice;</hi> and a <hi>ſtranger will they not follow,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41842:13"/> but will flee from Him,</hi> for they <hi>know not</hi> (allow approove not of) <hi>the voice of a Stranger.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fifthly, They are the <hi>Friends of Chriſt;</hi> that is the Relation<note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt. 7. 15.</note> they ſtand in to Him; now He walkes with them in His <hi>Galleries,</hi> and holds them there, while He openeth His whole ſoule unto them. <q>
                        <hi>All things,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>that I have heard of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I have made knowne unto you;</hi>
                     </q> An Admirable Scripture. Certainly Chriſt hath heard great things of His Father. He is the<note place="margin">John 15. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>wiſdome of the Father;</hi> He hath been with the <hi>Father</hi> from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity; and the <hi>Father</hi> loves Him; He will tell Him all the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things He hath in His Heart, and Chriſt will hide none of theſe things from His <hi>Friends.</hi> Judge you now how ſtrong the law of this Relation is with all His <hi>Friends;</hi> will they not deale friendly with Him? Thinke you: can they allow of any perſon, or thing, that offends His glorious eyes? will they be a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of His enemies? deriders of him, as the covetous are? A <hi>mans Companion is,</hi> (as he ſaith) the <hi>Counterpaine</hi> of himſelfe. <hi>Of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>San<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>: page.</hi> 173.</note> 
                     <hi>things Company is the worſt diſſembled,</hi> as that worthy man hath it from Excellent Learned <hi>Preſton.</hi> Truly they can <q>
                        <hi>ſay our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with His Sonne Jeſus Chriſt our Friend.</hi>
                     </q> And</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, Laſtly, He is their <hi>Shepheard,</hi> they His <hi>ſheepe;</hi> they heare Him, and follow Him in all things; And if they are as ſheepe without a Shepheard in ſight, They have an eye to ſee their <hi>great Shepheard,</hi> and <hi>over-ſeer of their ſoules.</hi> He hath undertaken for them, to follow them with <q>
                        <hi>His eye upon them</hi> (where ever they are, to <hi>deale well with them</hi> 
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 32. 8. Jer. 40. 4.</note>,)</q> and Him they will heare, and Him they will follow. An hireling they flie from, and with Goats they cannot mixe; In a word, and a plaine word; They are an abomination to the wicked, and the company of the wicked (viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly<note place="margin">Prov. 29. 27.</note> ſuch) in Church-Communions is an abhomination unto them. They feed in cleane Paſtures, upon the daintieſt meate provided for them; They love to feed together, to lie downe together, to walke together, for what Communion betwixt light, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Chriſt with Belial? with the wicked they cannot mixe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:41842:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>irſt, WE have heard, That the <hi>Law of the Relation of a Miniſter</hi> (for that one containes all thoſe dignities, glories, titles of honour, His Lord hath beſtowed upon him, calling them <hi>Angells,</hi> His <q>
                     <hi>par-Nymphs,</hi> or ſpokes-men to wooe and gaine the good will of ſoules towards Him; <hi>Ambaſſadours, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Stewards, Shepheards, Friends,</hi>
                  </q> we have heard how en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gageing all this is to a Miniſter to preach pure Doctrine, and to live an holy life, which they muſt doe, and cannot doe otherwiſe, having the <hi>Law of their Relation</hi> written upon their Hearts.</p>
               <p>Secondly, We have heard alſo how engageing the law of the Relation the people ſtand-in to their God in Chriſt, is, to them, being felt in them, written upon their hearts by the finger of God; they cannot but walke (this <hi>law conſtraining them</hi>) in the way of holineſſe, full-up to that Law, and their Rule, perfectly, and with a <q>
                     <hi>right foote,</hi>
                  </q> as to their courſe, and way, or walke, though through humane frailty, ſome of their ſteps may be out of the way.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>WEE come now to the third part of our undertaking, which was to cleare this <hi>way of the Holy</hi> from th' ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections caſt-in even by Miniſters themſelves, as well as by their people (in Common account Godly, as their people are) as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>ſcandalls</hi> or blocks, to keepe from entrance upon the way, or from a comfortable walking on-ward in it: And to tell our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation we have made from our eye and eare, this firſt we find objected.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 1. <q rend="margQuotes">It is an uncouth way; who or how few enquire after it, or tread in it? Not one Miniſter of ten, yet reputed Godly, nor one Man or Woman of twenty. Nay may we not ſay ſcarcely one Miniſter of an hundred, or ten of a thouſand among the common people? To this we reply.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:41842:14"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Granting what is ſaid and cannot be denied, for where ye heare the Miniſters <hi>contradicting,</hi> you ſhall heare the people <hi>blaſpheming,</hi> and this ye and we heare every where. But this proves the Holineſſe of the way, becauſe it is <hi>ſpoken againſt every where, contradicted and blaſphemed,</hi> Act. 13. 45. 28. 22. The <hi>way</hi> is as Chriſt Himſelfe was, a contemned, ſlighted perſon, <hi>who asked after him?</hi> and as the Church is, That walkes in it (which was ſaid) <q>
                        <hi>This is Zion, which no man asketh after,</hi> that is, <hi>very few,</hi>
                     </q>
                     <note place="margin">Jer. 30. 17.</note> But note it in paſſage, they that enquire not after this way, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire as little after Him, who is the <q>
                        <hi>way,</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>life;</hi>
                     </q> Who points His people to this way, leads them in it, and carryes them, as in His hand, to the end of the way, <hi>eternall life;</hi> But this can be no greife to us, nor offence of heart, That the <hi>way</hi> is ſo contemned, ſeeing <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſo ſlighted, and His Church ſo vilified; It is good to fare as Chriſt fareth, and His Church fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, The <hi>Spirit</hi> ſhall have the better cheare, if not at preſent, yet anone; <q rend="margQuotes">The way to Heaven is not the wide way of the world, which windeth to the Devill, but it is a ſtraight way, which few walke in, for few walke <hi>godly in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Holy <hi>Bradfords</hi> words.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 2. <q rend="margQuotes">Obſerve it well, and you ſhall ſee the pooreſt, and meaneſt of a pariſh goe this way, and but a ſprinkling of them neither, here one and there one, and yet ſo confident they ſeeme to be of their way, they would have all walke with them calling them to their foote.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Indeed they would (to ſpeake to that firſt) wiſh, as that all could <hi>propheſie,</hi> ſo all were as they are excepting their <hi>bands,</hi> ſcornes, and reproaches, though theſe they muſt meete with, if they will be godly. But they will never yeild unto any, <q>
                        <hi>That this is any other but an holy confidence,</hi>
                     </q> and their zeale for God, and love to His people, <hi>That all were the Lords people.</hi> They wiſh that they could ſpeake ſo gloriouſly of the Churches of Chriſt (we meane as to the numbers of them) as ye ſpeake of your Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous Church, <q>
                        <hi>They are all holy;</hi>
                     </q> every one of them, and borne to Church-priviledges; But yet they would account it almoſt <hi>blaſphemy</hi> to ſay ſo to them; Indeed they could wiſh they could ſee many <hi>wiſe</hi> men, and <hi>learned</hi> men, and <hi>rich men</hi> walking along with them; and yet, though they ſee it not; yet they ſee no cauſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41842:14"/> of diſcouragement though. The day is come, which was prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied off; <hi>The glory of Jacob ſhall be made thin,</hi> and <hi>the fatneſſe of</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 17. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>his fleſh ſhall be made leane</hi> (we take it we may allude to that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Relating there to a temporall deſolation, which followed) for indeed the <hi>wayes of Sion lye deſolate,</hi> and in compariſon, <q>
                        <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken; The wayfaring men ceaſe therein,</hi>
                     </q> and thoſe few that walke therein are counted the verieſt fooles in the world, (but by the fooles of the world, the wicked, and unreaſonable men there) It was ſaid of old, and it is the ſtumbling block ſtill, which fleſh and blood will never paſſe over. <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>Have any of the rulers, or of</hi>
                        <note place="margin">John 7. 48, 49</note> 
                        <hi>the Phariſees Beleeved on Him? But this people, which knoweth not the Law are curſed;</hi>
                     </q> They were a <hi>poore people</hi> ſtill, that ſaw their wants and were oppreſſed with them; who followed Chriſt; Theſe, and no other, except for His <hi>Loaves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They muſt be <hi>fooles</hi> (that is, they muſt know their owne wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to be fooliſhnes; their light darkneſſe; their ſight into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly<note place="margin">Iſa. 35. 8.</note> matters, blindneſſe; their ſtrength weaknes, yea rottenneſſe) they muſt <hi>be fooles,</hi> that walke in this way; <q rend="margQuotes">There is, as one ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 18. <hi>Hil:</hi> Joh. 4. 19.</note> a kind of kingdome, which (of all the corruptions that are in the nature of man) is the greateſt impediment, and bar unto ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace, and ſo to the walking in His way;</q> 
                     <hi>The</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>carnall mind, or wiſdome of the fleſh;</hi> It cannot endure this way being <hi>enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> it ſelfe againſt it; for ſuch it is againſt God. <q>
                        <hi>Thy wiſdome, and thy knowledge, it hath perverted</hi> 
                        <note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 47. 10.</note> 
                        <hi>thee;</hi>
                     </q> and it is noted as a wonder, "<hi>That a great Company of the Prieſts were obedient to the</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 6. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>faith;</hi> That the Carnall Miniſtery ſhould hearken after theſe things it were a wonder. Learned men and wiſe men after the fleſh, theſe are <q>
                        <hi>Lords</hi> they have no need of God,</q> they can live without Him; They bid, for the moſt part, defiance to Him, and His wayes; they would rather dye, than be pent-up in ſo ſtraight, and narrow a path: Indeed theſe Learned men (men puffed up with their Learning, theſe knowing men (but yet <hi>know nothing as they ought to</hi> 
                     <note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>know,</hi> thinking they doe know, and are lifted-up with that thought) theſe <hi>wiſe men</hi> are as brutiſhly ignorant, as we a brutiſh, and ſottiſh people are, at theſe two principall points; for how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle doe they know <q>
                        <hi>about originall and actuall ſinne,</hi>
                     </q> which is their diſeaſe? and how little <hi>about Chriſt,</hi> who is <hi>their Phyſician?</hi> theſe are Mr <hi>Burges</hi> his words. So then they, that are wiſe, and learned<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 41</note>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:41842:15"/> after the fleſh, muſt <q>
                        <hi>become fooles,</hi>
                     </q> that they may be wiſe, and taught to unlearne their Learning, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o any Confidence in that <q>
                        <hi>fleſh,</hi>
                     </q> before they can <hi>learne Chriſt,</hi> and know <hi>that they know Him,</hi> walking in His way. They to whom the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are revealed muſt <q>
                        <hi>be babes.</hi>
                     </q> By whom is not meant thoſe, that have no knowledge, or are <hi>Children in underſtanding,</hi> but ſuch as are <hi>lowly,</hi> and <hi>humble,</hi> and <hi>weake,</hi> comparatively with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſo carry themſelves, as <hi>weaned-ones,</hi> yet have their underſtandings opened, and have a ſaving knowledge of Him, <hi>Who is eternall life,</hi> and <hi>their life;</hi> And this may ſuffice to remoove that block of offence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 3. <q rend="margQuotes">The principles of this way are not peaceable, for we ſee what worke they make, and what differences are cauſed between Neighbours and Friends.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> We can ſay little to the <hi>peaceablenes</hi> of this way; we are verily perſwaded (which was more than once hinted before) fleſh and blood will find no peace, nor pleaſure in it. It is a way moſt<note place="margin">If you labour to doe the worke of the Lord, pray thinke it not ſtrange, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men curſes be your reward, and deteſtation your wages. Dr. <hi>Owen.</hi> Jer. 15. 19. <hi>Pag. 10. Cum ab homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur a Deo abſolvimur.</hi>
                     </note> croſſe or contrary to one principle at leaſt of Infant Baptiſme; And therefore ſeeing that is reported to be a <q>
                        <hi>peaceable princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> this <hi>way,</hi> and every ſtep in it,</q> ſtanding in the greateſt oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to it, as doe the remoteſt extreames, this <hi>way</hi> can have no peace in it, as the world calls peace, nor ſhall they have any peace from men, that preach-up this way, and walke in it. But we hope the way is not the more to be diſliked for this, but the more to be liked, and the rather to be choſen; It is condemned of men, it is approved of God: and that <hi>peaceable principle</hi> of Infant Baptiſme the more to be loathed. It is a way of holineſſe, elſe thoſe people, and Miniſters, that have the Law of their Relation written in their inward parts, would not walke in it. And Holineſſe we know with the way of it, is a meere <q>
                        <hi>contraction to fleſh, and blood,</hi>
                     </q> and a <hi>very torment</hi> to it, as fleſh and blood is a very bloody enemy to <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes;</hi> It would perſecute and drive <hi>holines</hi> out of the world, not thinking enough, if it could helpe it, to drive Holines out of the heart, whereat the fleſh is lifting every day, but conſcience holds it, and will not let the <q>
                        <hi>forme of it goe,</hi>
                     </q> the <hi>power</hi> was never there. Well; we grant that no <q>
                        <hi>principle</hi> of this way,</q> ſo far as we know, is <hi>peaceable;</hi> It yeilds no peace to the fleſh, but to the <q>
                        <hi>Spirit peace, peace.</hi>
                     </q> For being an holy or pure way, it muſt needs be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41842:15"/> 
                     <hi>peaoeable;</hi> firſt <q>
                        <hi>pure,</hi> then <hi>peaceable.</hi>
                     </q> O it is a peaceable way<note place="margin">James 3. 17.</note> to the Spirit; It yeelds more peace to the Spirit renewed, in one houre, than that <q>
                        <hi>peaceable principle of Infant Baptiſme</hi>
                     </q> can yeild the perſon all his life time. Nay, that peaceable principle is like to end in <hi>deſperate ſorrow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is no peace to this peace, to be ſubject to the <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>Prince of peace,</hi> the more ſubject thou art in thy walke to Him, the more <hi>peace</hi> ſhall be upon thee; The connexion of theſe two is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, <hi>Of the encreaſe of His government, and of His peace, there ſhall be no end;</hi> to ſhew, ſaith that Saint, on earth, now in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. <hi>Preſton.</hi>
                        </note> That as His government encreaſeth in mens hearts, and is enlarged, ſo as a man is made more ſubject to Him; ſo alſo <hi>peace</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 9.</note> encreaſeth. In thoſe, that are moſt ſubject, there is moſt peace, and therefore He is called the <q>
                           <hi>Prince of peace,</hi>
                        </q> for where He rules as a Prince, there is that peace, which He as a mighty Prince is able to procure to them. But He <hi>landeth</hi> upon the ſoule, as an Enemy, and with His ſword makes a Conqueſt there, before He is to that ſoule a <hi>Prince of peace.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 4. <q rend="margQuotes">This way cauſeth differences betwixt Neighbours, and Friends, whereas, obſerve it well, they that walke in the way of a Nationall Church, both Miniſters, and people, as Mr <hi>Hs:</hi> ſayes, and we find it to be juſt ſo, are very well accorded there is no difference between us.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> This makes for the way ſtill to be the <hi>way of Holines,</hi> and that other way to be the way of <hi>wickedneſſe,</hi> becauſe they are all (that walke in that <hi>broad way</hi>) ſo well agreed and accorded. We doe believe, That the verieſt <hi>varlet</hi> in the National Church agrees with Mr <hi>Hs:</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Prynne</hi> and <hi>John Timſon,</hi> and are all three all one as to that Doctrine of free admiſſion, <q rend="margQuotes">That all are to be admitted, even the worſt of all, to the Lords Table, ſo be they ſtand not excommunicated;</q> Theſe three are in one way, and of one judgement; how or wherein can they differ? I have, ſaid <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Non aliud ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bco robuſtius Argumentum.</note> no ſtronger Argument againſt the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>ſhavelings</hi> than this, That they are all agreed &amp; platted together like thornes <q>againſt Chriſt, and the offence of the Croſſe ceaſeth amongſt them.</q> This banding againſt Chriſt, and (though in other things they differ greatly) all true Chriſtians, hath accorded deadly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as once it did <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate;</hi> for upon the like account
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41842:16"/> 
                     <hi>they were made friends together, who before were at enmity between themſelves,</hi> Luke 23. 12. Truely we cannot readily find a more <hi>peaceable principle,</hi> raking in the dunghill of Popiſh ſuperſtitions, than is this, <q rend="margQuotes">That although the worſt of all, are to have free Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Lords Table.</q> The Miniſters of that perſwaſion hold to this; the people <hi>love to have it ſo;</hi> what diſagreement? For obſerve;</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Thoſe places, and perſons, and their way where their Religion is <hi>rivited-in</hi> by <hi>Infant Baptiſme;</hi> Obſerve it in villages, Townes, Cities and ſee how quietly and peaceably they live no difference among them in point of Church-Adminiſtrations. Then againe, obſerve thoſe places, where Religion hath been <hi>Rivited-in</hi> by <hi>preaching</hi> the Goſpell, the <hi>power of God to ſalvation,</hi> and ſee what deadly fewdes, and devilliſh differences there are there; oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by thoſe helliſh luſts in the hearts of men, which Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell-light comes to diſcover, and with a <hi>ſword</hi> in its hand to ſlay, and with <hi>fire</hi> in its mouth to conſume.</p>
                  <p>We would remember more of <hi>Luthers</hi> words here alſo; <q rend="margQuotes">If we were all quiet, and lived at peace one with another, while yet we live in our ſinnes, It is a ſure ſigne the Goſpel is not come unto us; or it be come it hath made no conqueſt over us: <q>it hath not throwne fire amongſt us, we have not felt it <hi>cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> like a ſword, making <hi>diviſion</hi> betwixt us, and our luſts; for how well accorded, and like Friends doe we live, while Friends, and well accorded with our luſts?</q> Truly, ſaid <hi>Luther,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Niſi tumultos iſtos vide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>em Chriſtum in mundo non crederem.</hi> Math. 10. 34. Luke 12. 51.</note> unles I ſhould ſee what I doe ſee, and heare what I doe heare, <hi>words</hi> like <hi>ſwords</hi> drawne out againſt God, and all good men, troubles, and tumults, and diviſions, I ſhould not beleeve the Goſpell to be in the world, for it brings a ſword with it where ever it comes, and cauſeth <hi>Diviſion;</hi>
                     </q> As we have read from our Lords own mouth, and ſo have we heard, and ſeene. It is notable if we can obſerve it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That the people of God were never vexed with more, and more ſtrange adverſities or grievances to the fleſh, than at that when the Lord Chriſt lived amongſt them; when were there more <hi>leapers, palſied men</hi> and <hi>women, lunaticks;</hi> and men poſſeſſed with Devills? ſo uſually it is with our Spirits, when Chriſt Jeſus our Lord lives within us; for He brings a <hi>ſword,</hi> and maketh <hi>Diviſion</hi> there; before He eſtabliſheth peace in our borders. We proceed-on here.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:41842:16"/>
                  <p>Tell us we pray you what difference have you obſerved, for we doubt not, but you have made your obſervation in the place where you were borne, betwixt Paſtor and people there; or in any other place, where you have made your obſervation, and there is <hi>like Prieſt, like people,</hi> as the one is, ſuch like are the other, and a juſt agreement betwixt them; for indeed what ſhould make diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence here in this broad way of the Nation? The whole Nation is Baptized and every perſon there; and now Religion is Rivited into them by their Infant Baptiſme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and thereby they are inſtated in, and poſſeſſed of all Church-priviledges, for that is the <q>
                        <hi>peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>principle</hi> thereof.</q> Certainly thoſe make-bates, the Spirit of the world without and that uncleane Spirit of man within will cauſe no difference there: They all goe-up to their meeting place, as friends, then up to the Lords Table, as <hi>Beleevers, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Saints,</hi> and in the After-noone to the Ale-houſe, if they pleaſe their <hi>Church</hi> will paſſe no <hi>cenſure</hi> upon them, what diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence can be here? for Aske them now, what they would have more to make <hi>peace</hi> amongſt them, and to take away all differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Their Miniſter will give it to them, having indulged them ſo much, if they can tell what they would have more, as to Church Adminiſtration; We te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> our perſwaſion, That Satan himſelfe, as to their Church matters, deſires no more, and he ſeekes their <hi>peace</hi> ſo far, that he will not diſquiet them; and therefore he will not viſibly appeare among them, though he is their <hi>God,</hi> &amp; <hi>Prinoe</hi> by <hi>choice,</hi> and the <hi>head of their company,</hi> amongſt whom there is ſo full a conſent, and no difference at all. To ſhut up this, The <hi>way of the holy,</hi> wherein Chriſt walketh with them, or in them, as they in Him, is as different from the way wherein the <hi>uncleane walke,</hi> as their perſon; are, ſo they looke not to the differences; They are no cauſe, but an occaſion of it <note n="a" place="margin">Every man ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ay. The occaſion, did b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t helpe, the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>incip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll; was my heart. Heb. 12. 14.</note> They <hi>follow peace with all men, and</hi> (giving a juſt offence to no man) <q>
                        <hi>holines, without which no man ſhall ſee God.</hi>
                     </q> Wee will take in here worthy M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Mantons</hi> words. <q rend="margQuotes">All true peace, and ſweet agreement, is founded in <hi>puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>holines,</hi> which meekneth ſpirits; And the pureſt, and ſweeteſt agreement is in the truth. Firſt there is <hi>a pure lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> and then one <hi>ſhoulder,</hi> Zeph. 3. 9. One faith is urged by the Apoſtle, as the ground of union, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. He will bring it to that at length; The world looketh at purity as the <hi>make-bate,</hi>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:41842:17"/> but it is the great <hi>reconciler.</hi> The world would have ſtirres end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they would have no difference in Church matters, neither would they have <hi>holines;</hi> So in thoſe matters they muſt be well accorded amongſt themſelves. But the counſell is ſeaſonable, <q>
                        <hi>Have ſalt in your ſelves, and peace one with another,</hi> Mark 9. 50. Doctrine muſt be kept wholeſome, and Truth retaine its ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and acrimony, and then looke after Agreement.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Certainly where God hath put enmity between thoſe, there will be a difference whileſt the world ſtands; what a difference? what a war? what a contention? what a bloody field is fought within the boſome of ſome Godly perſons at all times? If not of every Godly perſon ſometimes? <q>The fleſh fighting againſt the Spirit,</q>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 17.</note> the Spirit againſt the fleſh, for theſe <hi>two are contrary; <q>The car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</q>
                     </hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>mind is enmity againſt God,</hi> for <hi>it is not ſubject to the Law of God, neither indeed can be.</hi> You may as well perſwade darkneſs to ſhine, as the fleſhly mind to obey, and be at peace with the ſpirit of the mind renewed. When all differences are accorded, betwixt righteouſnes, and unrighteouſnes; Truth and falſhood, ſo as theſe may kiſſe, and embrace each other; When Chriſt, and <hi>Belial;</hi> Earthly <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſpirituall <hi>Adam,</hi> when theſe ſhall meet and comply each with other; Then ſhall the broad way, and the narrow be accorded too, and no difference between the walkers therein. There is no more ſure ſigne of an <q>
                        <hi>holy way,</hi>
                     </q> than that the <hi>unholy</hi> differ from it, come not neare it, turne their backe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and <q>
                        <hi>paſſe away</hi> as they ſhould doe from ſinne,</q> turne from it as an abhomination.</p>
                  <p>That is an <q>
                        <hi>holy way</hi> ſure; whereto the wicked ſtand ſo croſſe,</q> and contrary. Let our ſoules chooſe, and delight in the choice of that <hi>way,</hi> which is an <hi>abhorring to the fleſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 5. <q rend="margQuotes">Yea, but they That pretend to this <hi>holy way,</hi> and to walke in it, make it but a pretence ſure; They are quite out of the way; for obſerve how ſupercilious they are, and cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, they paſſe by others with a kind of ſcorne, bidding them as they bid, <hi>ſtand by,</hi> come not neare us, for we are <hi>holier, than you.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this we will ſay, this firſt; That looke what a <hi>man is in being he is in working;</hi> the meaning is, If his being is in Chriſt, his walke is in Chriſt; If he be out of Chriſt, he is without God
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41842:17"/> in the world, and his walke is <hi>after the fleſh,</hi> and according to the world moſt contrary to Holines.</p>
                  <p>But for this holy man, that walks in the wayes of holines; In deſire and endeavour his converſation is moſt exact, and pure; And of any ſin, though he cannot ſay he is free from any, yet he can ſay his ſoule abhorres the leaſt ſlighting, much more the ſcorning of any, be he or ſhe never ſo bad; Oh no, they that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with him are his witneſſes, and God alſo, that he is ſo farre from ſcorning, or ſlighting of others, that he is more enclined to <hi>mourning,</hi> than to <hi>ſcorning;</hi> he can mourne over the <hi>Contrary minded,</hi> and, if he might be ſuffered, he would rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oove them for their contrary walking, <q>
                        <hi>even weeping,</hi>
                     </q> letting as many teares fall from his eyes as words from his mouth; or when his eyes are dry his heart mournes, or he wiſheth it might be ſo; <q>
                        <hi>And groanes from the heart, are as acceptable as teares from the eyes,</hi>
                     </q> as was ſaid: <hi>periſhing for ever</hi> is ſuch a mournefull, dreadfull thing to his thoughts; He conſiders withall, <q>
                        <hi>who made the difference?</hi>
                     </q> and what hath he, that he hath not received? then why ſhould he glory either in himſelfe, or over others? No he that walks hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with his God, cannot walke proudly before others; he is meeke, and gentle towards all, <hi>waiting when God will give repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is one <hi>conſideration,</hi> and <hi>two Scriptures</hi> amongſt many, which the <hi>good Spirit</hi> hath brought home unto this man, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon his heart; whence it is he walkes humbly, loathing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and admiring free grace.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Conſideration</hi> is, That all the Sonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> by nature<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Brinſley.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">are, as one ſaith, <hi>like ſo many carkaſes buried together in the ſame Church-yard, or lying together in the ſame Golgotha,</hi> or <hi>Calvery,</hi> theſame <hi>Charnell houſe.</hi>
                     </q> Now this man, ſuppoſe it ſo, hath<note place="margin">Joh. 5. 25.</note> heard the voice of the Son of God in the Miniſtry of the Goſpell, and now he is <hi>riſen from the dead,</hi> for <hi>Chriſt hath given himſelfe;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 14.</note> Surely he hath no cauſe of glorying over his brother, that may lye ſtill rotting in that grave, but infinite cauſe hath he of <hi>glorying in his God</hi> all the day long, <hi>who hath made ſuch a difference,</hi> 
                     <q>even <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it pleaſed Him;</hi>
                     </q> whereas, as to outward accompliſhments, and naturall endowments, his brother might be like a flouriſhing <hi>Bay-tree,</hi> and he a poore ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>b, or <hi>bramble-buſh:</hi> His pride were<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4. 14.</note>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:41842:18"/> intollerable, that out of a <q>
                        <hi>priſon cometh to reigne,</hi>
                     </q> or of a deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable wretch, is new become <q>
                        <hi>Prince in all Lands;</hi>
                     </q> This is the<note place="margin">Pſal. 45 16.</note> humbling conſideration, <hi>He hath regarded the low eſtate of His handmaiden;</hi> 
                     <q>The well minding an oppreſſing <hi>Egypt,</hi> and an<note place="margin">Read Holy Mr <hi>Sanders, p</hi> 103.</note> howling wildernes, will keepe the heart very low in <hi>Canaan.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Scriptures are theſe, <q>
                        <hi>And ſuch were ſome of you,</hi>
                     </q> 1 Cor. 6. 11. Obſerve we well what ſome of them were: <q>Speake evill of no man, be no brawlers, but gentle, ſhewing <hi>all meekneſſe unto all men:</hi>
                     </q> why? <q>
                        <hi>for we our ſelves alſo were</hi> &amp;c.</q> 
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 2, 3. Wee thought it fit to be the longer here (though indeed we haſten to an end) becauſe we find good Mr <hi>Baxſter</hi> after his manner, deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not ſo kindly, as became him with the people of God, at this point, and in theſe words; <q rend="margQuotes">I confeſſe I have no great zeale to ſhut Chriſt out of all other Societies, and coope Him up to the Congregations of theſe few, that ſay to all the reſt of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſtand by, we are more holy than you.</q> Theſe words are in his Preface to Mr <hi>Hotchks</hi> his Treatiſe <hi>of forgivenes of ſins,</hi> where they ſpeak very worthily each of other; He dips his pen in the ſame gall writing to the <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> 
                     <q>The Phariſees liturgie is of too frequent uſe in the ſeparated Congregations [<hi>I thanke Thee (O God) that I am not, as other men are</hi> &amp;c. <hi>nor even as this Publican</hi>]</q> Thus he ſpeaks <hi>not making a difference.</hi> It might be eaſily ſhewen here, That this good man frequently wounds the moſt eminent Men amongſt us for <hi>learning</hi> and <hi>pietie,</hi> through the ſides of <hi>Separatiſts, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomians</hi>—But we proceed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 6. It is ſaid, <hi>This way of the Holy is a cloyſtered way.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> We ſay that reaſonably this cannot be ſaid againſt it. For how doth it appeare? They can ſay here much after the words their Lord and Maſter ſpake;; <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>I ever taught in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">John 18. 20.</note> 
                        <hi>and in the Temple, whither the Jewes alwayes reſort, and in ſecret have ſaid nothing?</hi>
                     </q> We may, we hope give-in curious <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> his gloſs upon this (we meane in point of expreſſing himſelfe by his pen) <q rend="margQuotes">underſtand Him, that He never wilfully affected Conventicles, as aſhamed of his doctrine, or willingly declined the Temple, when afforded convenient entrance thereunto; otherwiſe He taught alſo on the Mount, in the Ship, in Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, in private houſes.</q> The Godly Miniſters may ſay much
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41842:18"/> the ſame; They preach in the publique place, on the ſtated day; and it grieveth them to ſee how thin their Congregations are, yet when they are thinneſt, and they have feweſt hearers, even then they know their Lord hath ſewer; Though indeed the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple come more willingly to the publique place, for they Idol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ze places ſtill, as they doe their duties and their ſins, very ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious that way; they chooſe to pray, and to heare chiefly in the publique place, what they doe in the <hi>cloſet,</hi> God knowes; It ſeemes but little, or to little purpoſe, by that they doe in point of prayer in the open place, and in point of practiſe at home, and abroad, which is with moſt as contrary to the Rule of Gods word, as if they never heard a Sermon, or the <hi>word of life</hi> preached unto them: But we were ſaying, they doe not cloyſter up themſelves, nor their Doctrines, They are not, as a 'Candle under a buſhell, but on a Candle-ſticke, and <q>
                        <hi>ſo would give light to all that are in the houſe.</hi>
                     </q> If they ſpeake in a private place, as ordinarily they doe, and muſt ſo doe, come-in to heare, as many as will, the more the more welcome. They make a ſeparation no where; but at the <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt</hi> (as they may ſee cauſe and warrant from the beſt, and beſt learned, <hi>Calvin, Perkins, Ameſius</hi>) and the <hi>Lords Table,</hi> there they depart from the world. And there they have as cleare a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to doe it: <hi>viz:</hi> to keepe <hi>Dogs</hi> from taking <hi>holy things,</hi> as they have for ſtaving off a Dog from flying in their faces, or from leaping-up their Table.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>You will ſay what? before the Church hath paſſed their Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure on them, and declared them to be Dogs?</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was ſaid before; Chriſt will neither wait the leyſure of the State nor of your Church; He hath given power into His Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters hand to doe if not more, yet as much as that, To keepe the wicked from communicating in holy things; The manner of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſters in ancient times, as auncient Records tell you; ſurely even in theſe matters it may be ſaid as we read; <q>
                        <hi>The Remnant of</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mich. 5.</note> 
                        <hi>Jacob ſhall be in the midſt of many people, as a dew from the Lord, as the ſhowers upon the graſſe, that tarryeth not for man, nor wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for the ſons of men;</hi>
                     </q> ſo we have concluded, That godly Miniſters have as ſure a warrant to keepe out dog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and ſwine from commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating in holy things, as any man hath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from keeping a dog from flying in his face, or a ſwine from entri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g his cloſet; and if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e feeles
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41842:19"/> the power of this Relation upon his heart, he will find power e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in his hand intruſted there by his Lord and Maſter Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo to doe; and not to waite the <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Churches</hi> leyſure, what they will doe: Their Lord hath given them a <hi>key,</hi> and they muſt give it their hand; He power to them, they muſt put it forth for them, and if not here at the Lords Table, then no where, the <hi>key is of no uſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E come to that, which the great Devider, that <hi>Selah-Hammalekoth,</hi> if we may expreſs it ſo, that <hi>rock of Diviſions</hi> betwixt perſon and perſon, people and people. Thus it is objected;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 7. <q rend="margQuotes">The people of God, as they call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, make a ſeparation from others, theſe ſhall not come to them, they will not come to theſe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>We will heare what two ready Scribes, well <hi>inſtructed both unto the kingdome of heaven,</hi> have ſaid to this <hi>Dividing</hi> thing we call <hi>ſeperation.</hi> We will ſet downe what that holy and learned man ſaith, who ſpeakes much in a little, contracting, as we may ſay, the <hi>ſpirits of a point</hi> into a few words, which are theſe; <q rend="margQuotes">Sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">Eſchol, p. 51, 52, 53.</note> generally heares ill in the world; and yet there is a <hi>ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> ſuitable to the mind of God: He that will not ſeperate from the world and falſe worſhip, is a <hi>ſeperate</hi> from Chriſt. Now the ſeperation here commanded from any perſon, is not in reſpect of naturall affections, nor ſpirituall care of the good of their ſoules, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 3. Nor yet in reſpect of Duties of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 13. Nor yet in offices of love and Civill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, 1 <hi>Cor. 5. 10. 1 Theſ.</hi> 4. 12. Much leſs is not ſeeking their good and proſperity, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1. or not communicating good things unto them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 10. or living profitably and peaceably with them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 18. But in (1) Manner of walking and converſation, <hi>Rom. 12. 2. Eph.</hi> 4. 17, 18, 19. (2) Delightfull converſe and familiarity, where enmitie and oppoſition appeares, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. (3) In way of worſhip and ordinances of fellowſhip, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 4. Theſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41842:19"/> three, and the like commands and diſcoveries of God are moſt expreſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Neceſſity abundantly urgeth it, ſpirituall profit, and edification no leſs requires it. Cauſeth ſeperation from eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Churches, walking according to th' order of the Goſpel (though perhaps failing in the practiſe of ſome things of ſmall concernment) is no ſmall ſin: but ſeperation from the ſinfull practiſes, and diſorderly walkings, and falſe unwarranted wayes of worſhip in any, is to fullfill the precept of not <hi>partaking in other mens ſins.</hi> To delight in the company, fellowſhip, ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and converſe of unſavoury diſorderly perſons, proclaimes a ſpirit not endeared to Chriſt. So far that Holy and learned man.</q>
               </p>
               <p>We will make bold alſo to ſubjoyne worthy Mr <hi>Ant: Palmers</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 165.</note> words, which are theſe in the ſecond part of his Anſwer to Mr <hi>Hs:</hi> objection againſt <hi>ſeperation</hi> from the wicked, unleſs in caſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">What if a Congregation be ſo leavened with Cuſtomary ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and profaneneſs, and ſcoffing at Holineſs (as it is too too eaſie to find ſuch; nay where may one find better in the ſtate they are now-in) and a godly preacher comes to this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and a few Godly own him; Muſt this preacher and thoſe few Godly be enforced to communicate with ſuch? (after due meanes uſed for the inſtruction of the reſt) or may they not withdraw from the reſt who are ſcoffers at Godlineſs? ſure we beleeve God and Angels and Saints will juſtifie ſuch a ſeperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this ordinance, and to draw into a cloſſer communion to practiſe Diſcipline among themſelves, ſpecially while ſuch a Congregation was never orderly united, and joyned, together by a free ſubmiſſion to the Goſpel, having in moſt places never enjoyed it in the power of it; which Conſideration indeed, wipes off many objections.</q> So far that worthy man.</p>
               <p>Truely, Reader, thou haſt the very marrow, and ſubſtance of the whole matter already. Yet becauſe we have made it our very work and buſineſs in this place to remove the ſcandalls in the way to this <hi>ſeperation,</hi> and the offences taken againſt it, and withall to ſpeak to the underſtanding or the ſimple, as we our ſelves are ſlow and dull to conceive; we take leave to proceed according to our propoſed Method, and this we would ſay firſt.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:41842:20"/>
               <p>Firſt, We take it from Holy Writ, That this muſt be, there muſt be a <q rend="margQuotes">ſeperation. For as holy <hi>Bradford</hi> ſaid, There are but two Maſters, Chriſt and Satan; Two kinds of people, righteous and wicked; Two wayes, the way of <hi>Holines,</hi> and the way of <hi>wickednes;</hi>
                  </q> Two manſion places, heaven and hell; Now it is not poſſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to ſerve both theſe Maſters; If you joyne to one, you ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate from the other: And as impoſſible for the one, and the ſame perſon to be holy, and unholy at the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me time, as it is to be in an extreate heate, and in an extreame cold at one, and the ſame time; As impoſſible to have our foote ſtand in both theſe wayes, as it is for one foote to tread Eaſtward, and the other Weſt; or to fixe one eye on heaven, and the other on earth. Impoſſible alſo that we ſhould arrive at heaven, when we ſaile with winde and tide hell-ward, as that one and the ſame way ſhould lead us to two d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent and contrary Manſion places.</p>
               <p>Hence then it muſt needs follow (to goe over this againe) that here muſt of neceſſity be a <q>
                     <hi>ſeperation.</hi>
                  </q> They that will with <hi>full purpoſe of heart</hi> ſerve their great Maſter the Lord Jeſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt, muſt turne their backes upon them, that will ſerve the other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; And <hi>ſeperate</hi> from them, as to any familiarity, or intimacie with them. They that are reſolved at this high point, <hi>they <q>will be holy,</q>
                  </hi> they have not a <hi>velliety,</hi> a faint wiſh, or cold deſire, but they will be holy, and walke holily; As the men of the world ſay, <q>
                     <hi>they will be rich,</hi> come on it what will,</q> they will be rich, though they make <hi>ſhipwrack of faith</hi> (the <hi>profeſſion of faith</hi>) and <hi>of a good Conſcience:</hi> what care they, they <hi>will be rich,</hi> though they <hi>pierce themſelves thorough with many ſorrowes;</hi> The others ſay, as reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely too, with the helpe of God, and bleſſing upon the meanes, they <hi>will be Holy;</hi> Theſe now muſt make a ſeparation from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. They cannot be holy, and unholy together; It is ſaid that ſeldome it is, that the inward and outward man proſper together; ſuch an enemy walketh and proſperity is to the ſoules weale. But certaine it is, holines, and unholines are ſo far from thriving together, that theſe would come no nearer together, than the Eaſt comes to the Weſt; Therefore the holy, and unholy muſt part, and ſeparate, as their wayes muſt part, and when they come to the end of their way, then there muſt be an everlaſting ſeperation, and as far, as heaven is from hell thoſe ſo ſeparated manſion pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. In the ſecond place.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:41842:20"/>
               <p>Secondly, Gods people muſt ſeperate, for He hath as <hi>marv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly ſeparated them,</hi> His <hi>gratious Saints,</hi> as He did between the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and <hi>Egyptians:</hi> Now, how unworthy had it been, and<note place="margin">Pſal. 4. 3.</note> unbecoming, for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to have mixed themſelves with the <hi>Egyptians? I will dwell in them,</hi> and <hi>walke in them, and I will</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>be their God, and they ſhall be My people; <q>Wherefore come out from among them,</q> and be ye</hi> ſeparate <hi>ſaith the Lord, and touch not the uncleane thing, and I will receive you; and will be a Father unto you, and ye ſhall be my ſons and daughters ſaith the Lord Almighty.</hi> As if the Lord had ſaid, not elſe; If ye expect I ſhould walke with you, ye muſt walke as is comely for ſons, and daughters, that looke to have that ſweet and comfortable preſence of God with them. If ye walke with the world, and as the world doe, that is famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly, and not having buiſines with them, nor with an intent to doe good unto them; If ye will walke with them, I will not walke with you ſaith the Lord. If ye will not ſeparate from them, I'le ſeparate from you, and <q>
                     <hi>woe unto you, when I depart from you.</hi>
                  </q> It is, as if a man ſhould be converſing with ſome naſty poluted Creature, while He is talking with the greateſt Prince on earth; or as if a Bridegroome to ſome great Princeſſe, ſhould be court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a ſtrumpet before his Ladies face; whence we conclude, That there is as good a warrant for Miniſters and people, that know the law of their Relations, to <hi>ſeperate</hi> from the Nationall Church, as they have to ſeperate from the world, and from <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon;</hi> God will have it ſo; If <hi>Iſhmael</hi> fall a mocking, out with him, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21. 9. 12. If they will <hi>ſeperate</hi> from Me, <hi>ſeperate</hi> ye from them. Gods people will doe as their Lord bids them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, We ſay that Godly Miniſters, and their people can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid ſo much to make <hi>a ſeparation</hi> from the wicked, as theſe from them; The wicked will have no communion with godly Miniſters or people, unleſſe at the Lords Table, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at a feaſt of wine, and ſtrong drinke, we meane, where the fleſh is feaſted, no where elſe, they abhorre all other communions. You muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with them in ſin, elſe they will have no Communion with you; The world loves to Converſe with whom they love, <hi>their owne;</hi> And ſhould not they, that are choſen out of the world love to doe ſo too? The Godly need not ſeparate from the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41842:21"/> theſe will ſeparate from them; Theſe can endure holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany no more, than they can endure <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> which they have perſecuted out of their houſe, and would perſecute it out of the world; And ſhould theſe be admitted to partake of holy things, who perſecute holines, and will Communicate with you no where elſe, but at the Lords Table? and if not there, no where, And why ſo willingly, and chearefully there? to ſpeake that by the way.</p>
               <p>Holy <hi>Bradford</hi> gives you, we thinke, the Reaſon of that, wherefore your people are ſo ready to Communicate with you at the Lords Table? onely what he ſpake of the <q>
                     <hi>Maſſe,</hi>
                  </q> we may ſpeak of the Lords Supper (as to that we are ſpeaking off, and contending againg) <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>The Maſſe will not bite the people, nor make them to bluſh.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <q>Nor will this Sacrament of the body and blood of Chriſt, but the word preached will doe it, if it be heard, and obeyed, it will bite, and make us bluſh, it will cut like a <hi>ſword,</hi> and burne like <hi>fire,</hi> it will <hi>torment</hi> the fleſh, therefore the wicked will not come at it, if it be not a <hi>toothleſſe preaching;</hi>
                  </q> but if it bite they will bite the preacher, at leaſt ſnarle upon him, ſhewing their teeth, or turning their backes upon the word; but ſetting their faces to the Lords Table, thither they will haſten, there being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (now that the word preached hath not done its worke) that can trouble them, or make them aſhamed; <q>
                     <hi>They may come De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills to it, and goe home Devills,</hi> for <hi>no man finds fault,</hi>
                  </q> ſaid that Bleſſed man; The wicked converſe with none but thoſe, that are like themſelves; ye ſhall find them ſtill <hi>platted together like thornes;</hi> ſurely it gives a great leſſon to the godly, tells what they ſhould doe—but we proceed, And</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Take leave to tell you our perſwaſion, that if the Miniſters ſhall make no <hi>difference</hi> here between the <hi>pretious,</hi> and <hi>the vile,</hi> but deale forth to the one, as to the other at the Lords Table, the godly in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> all the truly godly all over the Nation will be <hi>gleaned</hi> forth from them, ſhortly, they ſhall not have one among them to Communicate with them. For if, as is recorded of <hi>John,</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">he would not come unto the <hi>Bath</hi> where <hi>Cerinthus</hi> was, that Blaſphemer; Can we thinke that the godly in Chriſt Jeſus truely and indeed ſuch will Communicate among you, who admit as vile, loathſome, and abhominable perſons as <hi>Cerinthus</hi> was, for you admitt all, <hi>if not excommunicated.</hi>
                  </q> We will
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41842:21"/> ſhutt up this with a Complaint we have read, or heard off: <q rend="margQuotes">where is now the zeale of former times? the Communion of Saints? the heating and whetting of one another by mutuall exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? where is the boldnes for the Lord? we have the light of thoſe times much encreaſed, but the heate much abated; their light was burning, ours but ſhineing at the moſt, and for the moſt part; <hi>Ignis, qui in illis calidus in nobis lucidus tantum.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, In the fifth place, and to ſpeak that more fully out, which was hinted before in the ſecond Paragraph. They that <hi>work righteouſneſſe</hi> can no more (upon choice) mixe with <hi>the workers of iniquitie,</hi> than they can mix with their works. For their Lord, having <hi>ſet apart</hi> (marveilouſly ſeperated, or made wonderfull)<note place="margin">Exod. 33. 16. Pſal. 4. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>him, that is Godly for Himſelfe,</hi> hath given to this <hi>ſeperated</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon a principle of His own, even His own Spirit, to enable him to <hi>ſet apart,</hi> that is, to conſecrate, dedecate devote or ſanctifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and his All to God; To live all the dayes of his life as a ſanctified or <hi>ſequeſtred</hi> perſon to God, and His ſervice; and from wicked wayes and companies. <hi>Be ye ſeperate, and touch no uncleane</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5. 48. 1 Pet. 1. 14, 15</note> 
                  <hi>thing,</hi> 2 Cor. 6. 16. God by His Spirit and Word, hath made them like Himſelfe <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>Holy</hi> in their degree and meaſure, as He is <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>Holy</hi> above all meaſure. Theſe people are by way of ſimilitude, likeneſſe, or reſemblance, the <hi>Image of God</hi> being renewed, and ſtamped upon them, as their <hi>God</hi> is, therefore they cary themſelves <hi>God-like; Godlineſſe</hi> being nothing elſe but a <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likeneſſe;</hi> So that as it is ſaid, <hi>There is none like unto the God of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurun:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 33. 26. 29.</note> ſo alſo is it ſaid in the ſame place; <hi>Who is like unto Thee O people ſaved by the Lord? There is none like Thee, O Lord God,</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi> It followes, <hi>What Nation is like Thy people, even like</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 7. 22, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſrael?</hi> And hence it muſt follow, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, ſpeaking of Gods people, <hi>So ſhall we be ſeperated, I and Thy people, from all</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 33. 16, Num. 22. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>the people that are upon the earth;</hi> and, <hi>they ſhall dwell alone, and ſhall not be reckoned among the Nations.</hi> The ſumme is this, They that are made like God, they cannot, upon choice, familiarly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with, and delight in the company of the wicked; A ſeperate people, whom the wicked-one ſhall not touch, muſt <hi>touch no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, In the laſt place, we would remember, what two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſaid in their Conteſt for the Truth, and againſt the oppoſers
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41842:22"/> thereof, and apply it to our ſelves; <q>
                     <hi>Though,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I cannot diſpute, yet I can dye for the Truth.</hi>
                  </q> The other, <hi>though,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I cannot unfold Popiſh Arguments, yet I have two maine grounds up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which I can ſtand, and bid defiance to Popery,</hi> to the Pope, his Jeſuits, and all the Papiſts in the world, <q>
                     <hi>Equivocation,</hi> and the <hi>Powder-plott:</hi>
                  </q> So, though we can doe little by way of Argument <hi>pro,</hi> or <hi>con,</hi> as they ſay, yet we have two grounds upon which we ſtand reſolved to bid defiance to Church Communions with thoſe that ground all they doe, as to thoſe <hi>ſigneing,</hi> and <hi>ſealing</hi> ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, or Goſpell Adminiſtrations upon the Principles of Infant Baptiſme onely; (1) The firſt ground is, They have no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (that ever we could meete with) but from fleſh, or fleſhly reaſon to draw us to it, or perſwade to a likeing of it: <q rend="margQuotes">Now fleſh<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Owen, Sanits perſev: p. 298.</note> is not onely a <hi>foole,</hi> but <hi>folly</hi> it ſelfe; not to be <hi>cured,</hi> but <hi>killed;</hi> nor <hi>ſtirred</hi> up, but <hi>mortified;</hi> as that excellently Learned man ſaith; And carnall Reaſon, as it is the great Idol of corrupt hearts, ſo it is the feirceſt enemie of God, and His grace.</q>
               </p>
               <p>2. The true Church is Chriſts Bride, or Spouſe, your Church is not<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Turatio ſtulta es non ſapis quae Dei ſunt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luth: T:</hi> 3. 73.</note> the Bride of Chriſt, for would the Miniſters of your Church pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute her to—we will ſay no more, though if we ſhould ſpeake it-out it would be much the ſame, which holy <hi>Bradford</hi> ſpake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pope, and his Prieſts in his Letter to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, and Towne of Cambridge;</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Can the Pope, and his Praelates meane ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, which make ſo much of the wife, and ſo little of the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band? The Church they magnifie, but Chriſt they contemne, if this Church were an honeſt woman (that is Chriſts wife) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they would make much of the Husband Chriſt, and His Word ſhe would not be made much of them, and admit they know not what, or whom into His Chamber of preſence.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd now we thinke we have the hardeſt worke behind to make a ſweet and cordiall cloſe with the Truth, and one with the other, and all in Chriſt; yet why ſhould this be an hard thing, if we can approove our ſelves; (we take the boldnes to ranke our ſelves with you, ſo inferiour
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41842:22"/> though we be) <hi>lovers of peace, and truth, and Friends to Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> how can we be Adverſaries? not to ſay, enemies unto one another? We would have our Lord Chriſt call us Friends, and deale tenderly with us, we muſt then more than ſhew our ſelves friends, and accordingly deale one with another; we muſt deale faithfully. So deale with us, we pray you, as you may ſee cauſe; Reproove us, rebuke us, we ſhall take it as a great favour, as an excellent oyle from you, which ſhall not breake the Head, as a fruit of your love cheifly, as the caſe may be, ſhewen in Rebukes, though yet we thinke it not comely to returne love for love, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the lownes, and meanneſſe of our perſons; yet we ſhould faile in our Duties, and Chriſtian offices we owe to each other, if we ſhould not tell you our feare at leaſt, that the Lord our God hath a quarrell with you; give us leave Deare, and Honoured Sirs to tell-out our feare, and what makes us to feare.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>WE thinke <hi>Heldegardis</hi> her propheſie lookes very wiſtly towards you, as bended againſt you. <q rend="margQuotes">The Maſters like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and Prelates doe ſleepe, deſpiſing juſtice, and laying it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide. A little after, in a certaine viſion, the Church appeared to her in the ſhape of a woman complaining, That the Prieſts had bewrayed her face with duſt, and rent her coate, and that they did not ſhine over the people, neither in Doctrine, neither in example of life; And for theſe horrible crimes and impieties, ſhe threatneth and propheſieth unto them Gods moſt heavy wrath, and dolefull puniſhments.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>This propheſie ſhall be to them that hate the Lord, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation thereof to His, and our enemies; That ye may not be found in the Number of theſe, nor be dealt with according to their meaſures, as theſe ſhall be dealt withall, we take the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to Commend unto you certaine heads of Conſideration.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That the day is haſtning when your worke ſhall be made manifeſt, and tryed as <q>
                        <hi>by fire;</hi>
                     </q> Ye ſhould feare at the thoughts of the judgements, which is written, and ſhall certainly fall upon thoſe, who have polluted His Sanctuary, done violence to the law of His Houſe, <q>
                        <hi>That none that were uncleane in any thing ſhould
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41842:23"/> enter in there.</hi>
                     </q> Ye have ſuffered perſons <hi>not ſeparated from their fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines</hi> to eate and drinke in His holy place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ye will not bring ſwine into your Hall, yet you will bring them into your Lords chiefeſt roome, He hath viſible upon this earth. Ye may <hi>beare rule for a time by theſe meanes, the people<q> loving to have it ſo,</q>
                     </hi> To have their Naſty perſons and uncleane courſes dawbed, palliated, and covered over with plauſible names, and glorious titles; But <hi>what</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ius ſub <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cti p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>feſſione pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>v:</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>will ye,</hi> and <hi>they doe in the end thereof, when He ſhall be very jealous for His Name-ſake, and the Houſe of His Glory?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, Be pleaſed to Conſider, and ſhew your ſelves men, The Lord God of Hoſts, beholding the Seas of blood, and rivers of Teares, and hearing the cryes, ſighes, and groanes of all His <hi>deſtitute, poore,</hi> and <hi>needy ones</hi> in the three Nations, and all over the world hath rode <hi>upon the<q> heavens to the Helpe of His Church,</q>
                     </hi> and <hi>in His<q> Excellency on the skie,</q>
                     </hi> that is, He hath helped His Church ſpeedily, and ſhewed His ſtate, and magnificence, when He came ſo to helpe her, making His Arme bare of fleſh, bringing His people <q>
                        <hi>hitherto</hi> out of their <hi>Egypt:</hi> made His mighty ones tread upon the waters,</q> paſſe over mighty floods; leape over walls; skip over mountaines; breake bowes of ſteele, and barres of Iron; ſet their feete upon the neckes of their Enemies; <q>
                        <hi>Bind, deſtroy them,</hi>
                     </q> 
                     <hi>whoſe height was like the height of the Cedars, and were as ſtrong, and as well rooted, as the Oakes;</hi> 
                     <q>yet, <hi>deſtroy their fruite from above, and their roote from beneath;</hi>
                     </q> and it was done; The Lord gave His ſervants <q>
                        <hi>Dominion over the mighty,</hi>
                     </q> ſo as His Warriours might ſay, <q>
                        <hi>O my ſoule, thou haſt trode downe ſtrength.</hi>
                     </q> And all this in order to an <hi>Imperious Reformation</hi> anon, which will not leave an <hi>hoofe behind:</hi> and can onely anſwer the deſires of the faithfull (who cannot be content with an halfe reformation, no more than with an halfe Chriſt) And ſhall certainly be, even full-up to their deſire, ſo ſoone as He hath by His Spirit, and Word prepared them for it, who hath ſaid, <q>
                        <hi>He will give them an expected end.</hi>
                     </q> But now ſee what all is come to, if the people of God ſhould be at your allowance? They ſhould have a Reformation, which is a very deformation, Beareing onely upon the <q>
                        <hi>Principles of Infant Baptiſme.</hi>
                     </q> From this Reformation, though ye make the beſt of it, the Lord deliver us, ſay all the godly people all over the Land. It may ſerve your Church well enough: But is as contrary to the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41842:23"/> Church of Chriſt, as darknes is to light, hell is to heaven. And to A reſt your thoughts here, we will offer this more to your Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Be pleaſed to Conſider, That the Lord hath done for His people in theſe dayes, as once He did; <hi>He gave Egypt for</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 43. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>their Ranſome, Ethiopia, and Seba for them;</hi> So hath He done now; <hi>He hath given men for His Church, and people for her life;</hi> may we not conclude of theſe things in the language of the Prophet, <q>
                        <hi>who hath heard ſuch a thing? who hath ſeene ſuch a thing?</hi>
                     </q> Iſa. 66. 8. Surely we may ſay, as <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Iſrael; <q>
                           <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Hath God aſſayed to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e,</q>
                     </hi>
                     <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>and take Him a nation by Temptations, by ſignes, and by wonders, and by war, and by a mighty hand, and by a ſtretched A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>me, and by great terrours according to all that the Lord our God doth for us in England before our eyes;</hi> To take a Nation out of the midſt of a Nation is our caſe: A Church out of a Church we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad almoſt ſaid, but there ſome would be angry. If <hi>England,</hi> finding (as now it doth) her children ſtrugling in her wombe, ſhould goe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of the Lord, as <hi>Rebecca</hi> did, <hi>Gen. 25. 22. </hi>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>Why is it thus?</hi> The Lord may anſwer, as He did to her, Two Nations are in thy wombe, and two manner of people ſhall be ſeparated from thee; A Nation fearing God, and a Nation Blaſpheming God: a Nation ſeeking Reformation, and a Nation oppoſing Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</q> And then.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Conſider in the next place, whether ye have not, and ſtill doe mingle theſe Nations together? an holy Nation, and an unholy together? a Royall people, and a baſe ſlaviſh people, (ſlaves to their owne luſts) whether ye doe not mingle theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether? (if they will be mingled) at the Lords Table? between whom the Lord hath marvailouſly ſeparated; ſetting a <hi>Selah-Hammat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>koth,</hi> a Rocke of <hi>diviſions</hi> betwixt them; But we need not make a Queſtion here; ye have joyned theſe, making them to ſodder together, if they, the godly we meane, will take your liberty, and be drawne out to meete at the Lords Table.</p>
                  <p>And doe not charge us here we pray you, nor let the Reader ſo doe, That we in any of this have charged any of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Churches, no not yours, provided, ye come off clearely from the way, and judgement M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Humph:</hi> ſtands in, as ye would from a <hi>quag-myre,</hi> wherein ye are ſinking over head and eares: Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41842:24"/> Churches, we hope, are for the moſt part of them, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully adminiſtred and therefore cannot admitt of a mixt prophane multitude to the Lords Table.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, Be pleaſed to Conſider, and aske your ſelves what ye have been doing all theſe bleſſed times all along <q rend="margQuotes">while the <hi>Lord wonderfull in Counſell, and excellent in worke,</hi>
                     </q> hath been doing ſuch glorious things in all the peoples ſight, that are not blinded with light. Certainly the <hi>voyce of rejoycing and ſalvation is ſtill,</hi> as it hath been, <hi>in the Tabernacles of the righteous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And they are <hi>working together with God in His owne ſtrength,</hi> (who doth all) to helpe-on the glorious worke of the Lord, and carry it on to an <q>
                        <hi>expected end:</hi> ſo ſerving glorious providences,</q> their God inſtructing, and enabling them ſo to doe: Nor are they diſcouraged at all, but rather the more animated, and ſpirited to their worke in the power of His might, ſeeing the contrary work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings (which muſt be looked for in ſuch times) of the Devill, and Satan together with all his curſed Children. He hath great wrath now; (why ſo angry?) becauſe <hi>he knoweth <q>his time is but ſhort.</q>
                     </hi> We crave leave to put it to the Queſtion againe; What are ye do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now, about the worke we <hi>call <q>Reformation,</q>
                     </hi> to the Midwy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring, or bringing it forth into the world? doe ye a ſweate at this<note place="margin">Neh. 3. 20. a <hi>Neſcit tarda molimina ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſanctus. Qui non zelat, non a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> We doe not love reformation, if we have not zeale for it Satan endures no mediocrity nor will God; you muſt be wholy and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ely His<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or lot at all; your ove muſt be much, elſe He will account it no little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred; Not to love God and work for H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> in the ſame degree, hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, and height of love, as we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ought, is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Him.</note> worke? doe ye <hi>build earneſtly?</hi> as they at <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> wall, he was fyery hot at his worke, <q>
                        <hi>flagrante animo,</hi> as <hi>Junius</hi> tranſlateth it;</q> This worke will not be done elſe; As the Lord God hath a zeale at this worke, ſo have all His ſervants, they worke for God now, as the Devill and his ſervants worke againſt Him. The Devill knowes he hath but a little time, he will doe as much worke, as poſſibly he can, and he will doe it <q>
                        <hi>earneſtly,</hi> and preſently,</q> he will not delay a Minutes time, he ſees all will ſcape out of his hands elſe; ſee what preſent work he makes by the <hi>Ranters</hi> hands, and <hi>Quakers</hi> hands, and by the hands of the corrupt Miniſtry in the Land, that <hi>filth, garbage, and common ſinke all over the earth:</hi> ſee what worke he makes by them, in their Churches and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pells; And among the reſt ſee what worke he hath made by two at the leaſt, and indeed by all the carnall Miniſtery over the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Verily, Deare, and Honoured Sirs, ye muſt worke, as ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly for the Lord, and Chriſt, as the Devill doth now with all his fellow-helpers <hi>in this iniquity</hi> doe worke againſt Him.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:41842:24"/>
                  <p>Sixthly, In the next place be pleaſed to Conſider, what ye have been <hi>praying</hi> for all theſe times? ye love <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as ye have mourned for her; ye ſeeke for peace, and proſperity heartily, your peace here, and hereafter being involved therein; ye are <hi>fellow-Commoners</hi> with her; <hi>joynt-adventurers</hi> in the ſame Ship, on the ſame bottome, conſider againe, and againe what ye have been <hi>praying</hi> for all theſe <hi>tempeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ous times?</hi> when this <hi>Ship</hi> hath been in ſo much danger; ſometimes covered over with waves, <hi>toſſed with Tempeſts, <q>and not comforted;</q>
                     </hi> What? were ye ſleeping all that time, or were ye praying? We will take the boldnes to anſwer for you here, ſo be ye will make full proofe, that ye are the Lords Remembrancers, and then you can never hold your peace, day nor night; ye have <q>
                        <hi>enquired</hi> after the Accompliſhment of thoſe glorious things the Lord hath cauſed to be propheſied off,</q> and His people to pray for grounding themſelves upon His pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and His Oath; <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>The calling of the Jewes; The utter downfall</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>G: returne of prayers. Pag.</hi> 13.</note> 
                        <hi>of all Gods Enemies; The flouriſhing of the Goſpel; The full pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and liberty of Gods Ordinances; The particular flouriſhing, and good of the Society, and place ye live-in;</hi> all they whoſe hearts are right, have, and doe treaſure-up many ſuch prayers, as theſe, and ſow much of ſuch <hi>pretious ſeed,</hi> which they muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to have the Church (it may be) in after ages to reape;</q> We would adde to theſe Holy, and Learned Mans words, thoſe we read ſome leaves after, <hi>pag.</hi> 43. <q rend="margQuotes">That which was the Spirit of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication in a man, when he prayed, Reſts upon him, as the Spirit of <hi>obedience</hi> in his courſe; ſo as that Dependance he hath upon God for the mercie he ſeekes for, is a ſpeciall motive, &amp; meanes to keepe him fearefull of offending, and diligent in Duty to looke to his paths, to walke, and behave himſelfe, as becomes a ſuitour, as well as to come and pray, as a ſuitor.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>To apply theſe <hi>momentous</hi> and weighty words to our purpoſe. <q>
                        <hi>Ye pray for the calling of the Jewes.</hi>
                     </q> Then muſt ye pray for the remooving of that, which hath let<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed hitherto, and will let till it be remooved. Surely <hi>the <q>earth</q>
                     </hi> muſt be ſhaken firſt, all thoſe Crownes ſhattered to pieces, that will not be laid downe at the feete of Chriſt; The <q>
                        <hi>Heavens</hi> muſt be ſhaken too, elſe we are much miſtaken, all <hi>falſe Religions</hi> in the world,</q> how ſpecious ſoever in mans eye; <hi>Gods houſe muſt be ſwept too,</hi> and <hi>His floore
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41842:25"/> purged,</hi> from, you ſhould know what, becauſe theſe <q>
                        <hi>out-ſweep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> which muſt be, are your owne doings;</q> Then, Is your mind intent upon all this? as your mind is, ſuch your Prayers are, as to that matter.<q> 
                        <hi>Ye pray for the downfall of Anti-chriſt;</hi>
                     </q> Take heed, ye doe not in whole, or in part, hold that-up, you profeſſe to pray downe. Ye pray for the flouriſhing of the Goſpel, and that your labours therein in ſpeciall may <q>
                        <hi>be taking</hi> and <hi>prevailing</hi> with your people, that thereby <hi>life,</hi>
                     </q> 
                     <hi>and immortalitie may be brought to light unto their ſoules.</hi> Ye muſt not now practiſe croſſe to your prayers, ye muſt not obſtruct your owne way to the bleſſing ye ſeeke for: ye muſt not then give that to Baptiſme, which the Lord Himſelfe gives to the preaching of His Word. So much hath been ſpoken to this before, that we will adde little to it now, only this; Your Leaarned Brother feares not to tell us, <hi>we<q> owe our Religion to Infant Baptiſme.</q>
                     </hi> Truly we owe it, and give unto it as much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, we thinke; as he doth, or ought to doe, being an Ordinance of Chriſt, and to be adminiſtred according to due order, as He hath preſcribed in His word (which is we conceive to give due honour to it; yet we feare to ſay, <hi>we <q>owe our Religion to it;</q>
                     </hi>) no more than we owe our lives to that Maſter, who hath given us to weare his badge, or livery, we owe him all the ſervice that is due from a Creature to a Creature, but we owe our lives to God, our beſt ſervice, and all: ſo we owe not, as we conceive, <hi>our Religion to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Baptiſme;</hi> but to the glorious worke of the Spirit, together with the Miniſtry of the word; thereby, as an Inſtrument in the Spirits hand, <hi>He <q>Rivi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>s Chriſtian Religion into the body of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</q>
                     </hi> and <hi>into the hearts of His people,</hi> growne up to the yeares of underſtanding; <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Let the <q>Covenant be opened firſt, the abundant riches of grace therein, through Jeſus Chriſt; whereunto we owe our ſelves, and all, and the ſeales will follow of courſe;</q> We take leave to tell our perſwaſion: A godly Miniſter looſeth more by giving ſo much to Infant Baptiſme, than he will gaine by his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the ſucceſſe of the Goſpell, his God hath intruſted him with.</p>
                  <p>Againe, ye pray for the full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and liberty of Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, doe ye not? Take heed ye doe not <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut the ſinewe of this your prayer, and quite weaken it, by granting a liberty, <hi>free Amiſſion to all,</hi> whileſt you ſet <hi>parity</hi> aſide, as a neglected
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41842:25"/> thing, though it be the maine, even the all of the Duty. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ye ſhould ſtill, the one is to be as <hi>full</hi> as the other, <q>
                        <hi>full li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and as full purity.</hi>
                     </q> A liberty without purity will certainly bring us into ſtraightneſs of place (which we Engliſh <hi>anguiſh</hi>)<note place="margin">Rom. 2. 9.</note> ſuch as we cannot tell what to doe-in to get one minutes time of eaſe. If ye will give liberty, ſee it be ſtinted, and bounded within the bounds, and limits, which God hath ſet us; <q>
                        <hi>To keepe within the compaſſe of Gods Commands is the beſt liberty of all; Then ſhall I have liberty;</hi>
                     </q> when? <hi>when I keepe all thy Commandements.</hi> If we<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 45.</note> would have liberty out of God, and beyond His bounds, our <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> will proove our <hi>miſery,</hi> our undoing, and utter deſtruction. Looke ye to it, as ye looke God ſhould looke after you, and your prayers, That ye carve not forth ſo liberally in your Lords mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, granting to your people <q>
                        <hi>a full liberty</hi> without regard had at all to <hi>full purity</hi>—But having ſaid ſo much againſt your <hi>full liberty,</hi>
                     </q> and all thoſe impurities, which cleave as faſt to that <q>
                        <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</hi>
                     </q> as ever any did to their Idol, we will ſay no more here, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as ye goe on praying, ye will goe on ſinning, and provokeing your Lord to His face in His owne Houſe, if ye doe not looke better to His Adminiſtrations there, than hitherto ye have done.</p>
                  <p>Seventhly, Be pleaſed to Conſider, That the <hi>Body,</hi> whereof our glorious Lord is the <q>
                        <hi>Head,</hi> and the <hi>Saviour;</hi>
                     </q> is as like Him, as likeneſſe can be, a very comely, and a glorious Body; and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever little glory, or comelines may appeare from without, and none at all in the worlds eye, yet is ſhe<q> 
                        <hi>all glorious within</hi>
                     </q> (par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takeing of her Lords owne glory, though not in the ſame degree) and every one of this Mothers genuine Children are made<q> 
                        <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in all lands;</hi>
                     </q> where any one of them is, there is a<q> 
                        <hi>Prince</hi> how poore,</q> and meane ſoever the out-ſide be; for whatever the Lord-Chriſt is <hi>by</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>Nature;</hi> he and ſhe are <hi>by Grace:</hi>
                     </q> Conſider, we pray you, this thing, then we know what will follow upon this Conſideration, ſo be, ye be much, if not<q> 
                        <hi>wholy in it;</hi>
                     </q> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">That the fire will conſume all that is glorious in the world; yet a very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while, and there will be no excellencie but the excellencie of Chriſt, and His Church, and Children;</q> we are bold to preſſe you unto this Conſideration againe, becauſe ye, and we know what muſt needs follow thereupon.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:41842:26"/>
                  <p>Firſt, Ye will give the Lord Chriſt the preheminence in your aſſemblies, and at His Table ſpecially, ye will ſet His deare Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Beloved Friends, and faithfull ſervants next unto Him: And by no meanes will ye ſuffer that which may offend, or grieve them: And ye will ſtave off thoſe naſty filthy Creatures, two foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Dogs, and ſwine from comeing neare unto them, till they have bethought themſelves what they are, and of their uncleanneſſe; And</p>
                  <p>Secondly, As ye know, The firſt thing, the Spirit of grace doth within doores is to ſet God and Chriſt in His own place, the heart; ſo that perſon, that is acted by that Spirit will ſhew forth or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime Gods Juſtice in the world, and Chriſt His Righteouſneſſe in His Church, which is to ſet Him in His place, a <hi>King,</hi> and a <hi>Prophet,</hi> a <hi>Prince,</hi> and a <hi>Saviour,</hi> and perſwade an hearty obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſubjection to Him, to be directed by Him; for if a man be ſubject to Chriſts Kingly Office, His Propheticall office ſhall guide him, and cauſe him not to erre, in that he ſpeaks from God, or to God, or in what he is to doe for God, and His People.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E would give you two or three Scriptures to muſe upon; draw two, or three things from them, and then draw to a cloſe of all. The firſt Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52. 1. <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>From henceforth there ſhall no more come into them the uncircumciſed, and the uncleane;</hi> The like promiſe ye have, <hi>Joel 3. 17. So ſhall ye know that I am the Lord your God, dwelling in Zion, my holy Mountaine; <q>Then ſhall Jeruſalem be holy, and there ſhall no Stranger paſſe through her to defile her. No ſtranger?</q>
                     </hi> to open that notion, as we read<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>yl Job 15. p.</hi> 89.</note> it opened unto us;<q>
                        <hi>No ſtranger,</hi>
                     </q> that is, no child of <hi>Bolial,</hi> no wicked perſon, ſhall paſſe through her, to defile, and pollute her: But ſtrangers may paſſe through her to be viſited, and relieved by her.</q> The other Scriptures, <hi>Mal. 3. 16. <q>Then they that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lord ſpake often one to another:</q>
                  </hi> Acts 2. 42, 43. "<hi>They continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine, and Fellowſhip: And all that beleeved.</hi> 1 John 1. 3. <q>
                     <hi>Truely our fellowſhip is with the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41842:26"/> Father, and with His Sonne Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  </q> Rev: 21. 27. &amp; 22. 15. <hi>There ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any thing that defileth, nor what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever worketh an Abhomination; for without are Dogs, and ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and whoremongers, and Murderers, and Idolaters, And who ſo loveth, and maketh a lye.</hi> From the premiſed Scriptures we would Conclude. Firſt;</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>Firſt, THat it is one of the higheſt priviledges promiſed to the Church, that a time ſhall come, when the wicked ſhall not come unto her; <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>Awake, awake, Put on thy ſtrength O Sion, put on thy beautifull garments, O Jeruſalem, the Holy City.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the Holy City awake thus, and be ready in her dreſſe, in her beautifull garments? why? there is good newes for her, <q>
                           <hi>from henceforth, there ſhall no more come into thee, the uncircumciſed, and uncleane.</hi>
                        </q> As if He had ſaid, In times of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> defection, or oppoſition, when there was no due Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of worſhip, nor order among worſhippers, than the uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, and uncleane came, and ſtood, yea even dwelt with thee, as thy owne Children; but oh <hi>Jeruſalem!</hi> A Time ſhall come, when the uncircumciſed and the uncleane ſhall not ſo much, as come into thee, they ſhall be rejected, and caſt out for ever; Prophane ones ſhall find no place at laſt in <q>
                           <hi>Sion here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low;</hi>
                        </q> and Hypocrites ſhall never come into the <hi>Sion,</hi> which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove. Some Hypocrites will come into the Church, when ſhe is moſt refined, there is no keeping of them out, till they diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver themſelves, and ſo are caſt out, or Apoſtatize, and ſo goe out of themſelves: poſſibly the Church Militant may be ſo pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and reformed at laſt, that as there ſhall be no prophane in her, ſo but a few Hypocrites. But into the Church Triumphant, we are ſure, the cloſeſt Hypocrite ſhall not Enter: God will waſh off all the varniſh, and paint, which they have put upon the face of their profeſſion, with Rivers of Brimſtone, and will give them then, the cup of His fierce wrath to drinke unto Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</q> We have been the larger upon this Scripture, becauſe we find it ſo fully enlarged to our hands, and it was ſo good, and ſo full to our purpoſe, that we could part with none of it.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:41842:27"/>
                  <p>Secondly, Seeing this is the promiſe of God, and what He hath ſpoken with His mouth, He will fulfill with His hands, He will find faithfull men, who ſhall be His hands in all the peoples ſight, for this ſeparating, this reformeing worke, this making a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; They ſhall lay-out themſelves to the utmoſt of thoſe abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, their great Lord ſhall give unto them, That the Saints may enjoy unmixt Communions here below, and live together as if there were not another among them; we ſay, they ſhall endeavour this matter full-up to the promiſe, That the wicked, or<q> 
                        <hi>Belial</hi>
                     </q> (in the originall) he or ſhe, that will not beare the yoke of God, ſhall no more <hi>paſſe <q>through thee;</q>
                     </hi> much leſſe ſtay and lodge in<note place="margin">Nahum 1. 15.</note> thee; that is the promiſe; no man ſhall be yoaked with you, but<note place="margin">See the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition <hi>Job</hi> 19. 386.</note> he that beares the yoke of Chriſt. This will be the day of <hi>Sions</hi> glorious liberty, when all (within her liberties) beare the yoake of Chriſt, and none ſhall be unequally yoked; This is the glory of the Saints below, and this ſhall be perfect in the ſtate above, but all the faithfull in the land breath, and endeavour after this; and the more earneſtly, becauſe this is promiſed, and they thinke the<q> 
                        <hi>ſet time</hi>
                     </q> is haſtening, when it ſhall be performed; for they cannot doubt, but that there ſhall be as great a <hi>portion of the Spirit of holineſſe, and of unity,</hi> and as eminently powred out upon the Saints in theſe latter ages of the world, as there was upon the firſt Goſpell Church, <hi>Act. 2. 1. They were altogether in one place with one accord, as if they had all but one ſoule;</hi> and they continued in the Apoſtles Doctrine, ſo in fellowſhip one with another. And</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, That all the Godly, truely and indeed ſuch all over the land, Miniſters and people muſt make a difference, a ſeparation according to the Command of God, and the practiſe of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times all along upward to this day, as to the point of Church Communion and fellowſhip one with another; for as ſure as they are ſanctified ones, they are <hi>ſeparated</hi> ones, dedicated to God for the promoteing His glory, and carrying on the intereſt of Chriſt in their owne, and in the hearts of others; Man is a ſociable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note n="*" place="margin">Man would rather endure the greateſt miſery toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his friends, than enjoy the greateſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe by himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Dion.</hi> third Orat.</note>, he loves not to be alone, unleſſe he be in meditation; and he is not leſſe ſociable, becauſe he is more holy; but he is more choice of his Company, As every good man is, and ought to be, a mans Companion being (as was ſaid) <hi>a Counterpaine of himſelfe,</hi> he cannot now converſe among the wicked, upon choice and <hi>with
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41842:27"/> delight,</hi> (unleſſe he could convey good unto them) more than he could delight to be with thoſe poſſeſſed men among the Tombs, <hi>Mark.</hi> 5. 3. It is with the Saints now, as it was with the <hi>primitive Church,</hi> they <hi>aſſociated themſelves in thoſe dayes,</hi> ſo they muſt now; They <hi>continued in fellowſhip one with another,</hi> as well as in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Doctrine; ſo they muſt doe now: They were all of one mind, and therefore fit to make one body; ſo are they now, as to the maine, and principall things required of them, walking together in Church Communions, and Goſpell fellowſhip; <q>
                        <hi>The Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and fellowſhip of the Saints is the lower heaven of the Saints,</hi> as ſaith that worthy man; Therefore they can no more converſe<note place="margin">Upon <hi>Job</hi> 16. 54.</note> among the wicked upon choice, than <hi>David</hi> could chooſe to live in</q> 
                     <hi>Meſech,</hi> and <hi>dwell in the Tents of Kedar;</hi> A ſavage and wild people, without the verge of the viſible Church; ſuch company is like the torment once invented, of chaineing a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>live-man,</hi> and a <hi>dead-man</hi> together; The Godly in Chriſt Jeſus count it a great evill to be joyned with unſavoury dead wretches at any time, or place (much more will they avoide it where they can <hi>at the Lords Table,</hi> (the onely place the wicked will joyne with them in) <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> prayes,<q> 
                        <hi>Gather not my ſoule with ſinners,</hi>
                     </q> Pſal. 26. 9. If we would not have our ſoules gathered with ſinners hereafter, for the preſent we muſt take heed of joyning with them. <q rend="margQuotes">A good Gentlewoman, (as we have heard) being much troubled in Conſcience, and ready to goe out of the world, prayed thus; <hi>O Lord, let me not goe to the place, where the wicked are, for Lord, thou knoweſt I never loved their Company here.</hi>
                     </q> And this ye may have read alſo;<q> 
                        <hi>Looke with what Company we delight our ſelves-in here below, with them, we ſhall be, and converſe for ever, either in the higheſt heavens, or in the lowermoſt hell.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>We would adde this more, to confirme us in this Truth, That the righteous can no more, <hi>upon choice,</hi> be with the wicked, than ſheepe and lambs can be with grievous Wolves, and Tigers; looke, as of what nature the Appetite is, of the like nature muſt be the food. Carryon, or ſuch like filth will ſerve the Raven, not the Dove; earthly food will ſatisfie a naturall appetite, and heavenly food will ſatisfie the heavenly appetite, that, and no other; ſo <hi>looke of what nature the man is, the like ſhall his Companion be,</hi> if he may be at his owne choice, with whom he will have communion,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41842:28"/> ſpecially at the Lords Table. The meaning is, Saints deſire to feed with Saints, and they will feed with them at the Lords Table, elſe they will not come at it; They are as choice of their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as they are of their meate, in all places, but ſpecially at that place; They deſire to have Communion onely with Saints, and that the pretious may be ſeparated from the vile, that their feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may not be with grievous wolves, but with the harmeleſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and peaceable lambs of Chriſt; for if<q> 
                        <hi>Chriſt is the</hi>
                     </q> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and <hi>reſting place of all the affections of the Saints,</hi>
                     </q> as moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly He is, then muſt the Saints abound in love one towards an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, in, and for Chriſt, which they cannot evidence any other way, but by often meeting one with another, and ſpeaking one to another, and working one for another, what poſſibly they can. <q rend="margQuotes">We will put a cloſe to this in Bleſſed <hi>Sibs</hi> his words. Next to the meditation of Chriſt, and the Excellencies that are in Him, I know no way more effectuall, than is holy Communion with thoſe, that are led with the Spirit of Chriſt, when we ſee the ſweet fruite of it in others It hath been a meanes ſanctified to doe a great deale of good to many, and thoſe that delight not in it, never knew what the likeneſſe of Chriſt meant; for thoſe that deſire to be like Chriſt, they love the ſhineing of Chriſt in any. They are a careleſſe people to whom all companies are alike: But they that walke circumſpectly, looking round about, making it their onely care how to pleaſe God, theſe will make choice of thoſe, that find ſome worke of grace on their hearts by the Spirit of God; if not, they may well doubt of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and that there is no worke of grace wrought at all, <hi>for grace will make us love the like;</hi> As you ſee creatures of the ſame kind love to company with one another, Doves with Doves, and lambs with lambs, ſo it muſt be with the children of God, or elſe we do not know what the communion of Saints meanes.</q> In the laſt place, and in proſecution of that was laſt ſaid,</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, We Conclude, That the Saints loving, and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Communion together are fruitfull, and uſefull to one another, while they are together; and <hi>therefore doe ſpeake often one to the other;</hi> Thereby to <hi>ſtirre-up</hi> one anothers <hi>pure minds.</hi> And this is a Duty ſo cleared in the booke of God, to be according to the mind and word of God, to keepe off from the wicked, who
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41842:28"/> will keepe far off from God; And oppoſe the meanes whereby they may be brought nearer unto Him; It is ſo agreeable to the <q>
                        <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> and as we heard, <hi>the new creature,</hi>
                     </q> to converſe with their like, and ſo to walke together in Goſpell Order, that truly we cannot conceive what can be reaſonably ſaid againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t by any reaſonable man, ſpecially by Miniſters of Chriſt. Nay we are aſſured nothing can be reaſonably ſaid againſt it; True it is Miniſters in name ſuch, and godly by profeſſion, doe oppoſe this <hi>Aſſembling together of Saints,</hi> but they are aſhamed, no doubt, to ſhew ſo little reaſon, as to reaſon againſt it; For to gaine Inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from lower matters; Can we thinke, That the matters, or concernments of a pariſh are ſo conſiderable, That the chiefe men, or Maſters there with the reſt, muſt meete ſometime<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to conferre about them for the better diſpoſing of them, according to decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and right order? Can we thinke then, and thinke like men, that the matters of Chriſt, the concernments of His glory in our ſalvation, will not require the like care and ſo Command the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, <hi>Saints by calling,</hi> to meete often, and conferre about thoſe high, and ſacred matters, ſo nearely relateing to the welfare of that Body, whereof the Lord Chriſt is the Saviour, that theſe may be adminiſtred according to the mind of Chriſt, and rule of His word, praeſcibed by Himſelfe, to be obſerved in His houſe by His Stewards there? If they will make full proofe, that ſuch they be by <hi>fidelity</hi> as well as in <hi>Name,</hi> and <hi>by Office.</hi> Well, we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident our Lord and Maſter makes us ſo, (whoſe manner was to ſpeake alone, and apart with His Diſciples) ſo doe all thoſe, that have gone forth by the footſteps of the flocke, <q>
                        <hi>following His ſteps;</hi>
                     </q> That all thoſe Miniſters who oppoſe this Aſſembling of the Saints together, there to ſpeake often one to another for the ends aforeſaid, are <q>
                        <hi>ſelf-willed men,</hi> ſelf-will is their reaſon; ſo there is no argueing with them,</q> who have nothing to oppoſe againſt this <hi>Goſpell fellowſhip,</hi> but their <q>
                        <hi>will,</hi> or carnall Reaſon; onely we would commend them to the Prayers of the Saints;</q> And for thy ſelfe, Reader, if thou canſt skill onely in thy Mother tongue, we would Commend to thy meditation, that plaine Engliſh thou readeſt, <hi>Eph. 4. 16. <q>From whom the whole body,</q>
                     </hi> &amp;c. and if thou canſt skill in the Latine, Then we heartily commend to thee, Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Calvins</hi> three doctrines therefrom, and <hi>Beza's</hi> obſervations
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41842:29"/> thereupon, in his notes common with us, and in his larger Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions too large to be inſerted in this place.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>ANd ſo we make bold to give in our Jealouſie, which may paſſe for better Reaſon, than any <q>
                        <hi>ſelf-will</hi> can give;</q> why Miniſters, reputed Godly, plead for a looſe way of receiving all ſorts of perſons to Communion at the Lords-Table, and by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous admiſſions, proſtitute the Ordinances of Chriſt to every Commer, oppoſeing in the meane while what they can (as they muſt needs doe, allowing ſuch doings) the <hi>Communion of Saints here below, and fellowſhip one with another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, Is it not becauſe they would not diſpleaſe the people? leaſt thereby they ſhould open the peoples mouths againſt them, and ſhut their purſes? As certainly it would be ſo, for two footed ſwine, and dogs, who returne to their folly as thoſe foure footed ones to their vomit and myre, cannot endure to be called ſuch, and dealt with as ſuch in point of Church Communion. Indeed, as worthy Mr <hi>Manton</hi> ſaith; this pleading for a looſe way of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving<note place="margin">Epiſt: before Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> Booke.</note> all ſorts of perſons to holy things, <q>
                        <hi>Looketh as exactly calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated for a wordly intereſt.</hi>
                     </q> We charge you not ſo as he doth not; but we would charge you in the name of the Lord, ye would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine your ſelves, whether it be not ſo? And this we dare ſay to helpe you-on in your tryall, That as long as a mans heart is <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loving, and over-delighting in any thing but God,</hi> he ſhall doe little for God, perhaps much againſt Him: <q rend="margQuotes">For be he a man of great<note place="margin">Part. 2. 359</note> illumination, raiſed gifts (as worthy Mr <hi>Burgeſſe</hi> ſaith) and parts, whereby he is admired in the world, yet hath not a cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, and mortifyed heart; he cannot but pray, preach, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of thoſe things, which though not above his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet above his heart, and affections;</q> And then little can he, or will he doe for God in his owne private houſe, or in the houſe<note place="margin">I have had much to doe with my proud ſwelling mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d, my ſtiffe neck, and ſtubborne heart. <hi>Hier.</hi>
                     </note> of His God. Therefore we would adviſe others, as we doe our ſelves in <hi>Luthers</hi> words, <q>
                        <hi>If they would overcome a world of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies without, they muſt begin with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their maſter-luſt within, and when that Goliah is ſubdued, the Army is routed, and they will flye;</hi>
                     </q> This I know ſaith <hi>Luther</hi> by certaine experiences, <q rend="margQuotes">That I have
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41842:29"/> more cauſe to feare what is within me, than what is without; and I have hit the naile on the head, when I ſay <q>
                           <hi>venter in omni</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi non viden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> quaeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>um rident Chriſtum; ubi datur u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> edant add<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ci poſſunt ut credant. To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>no. <hi>upon Hoſ: 10. 11.</hi> Avari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>â eſt plerum<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinem comes ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, <hi>&amp;c. Ameſ. in pe:</hi>
                           </note> 
                           <hi>religione potentiſſimum Idolum,</hi>
                        </q> 
                        <hi>the belly ſwayes moſt in every reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; though where that is ſerved, Chriſt is deſtroyed, and they who make their belly their God, makes the Lord Chriſt but an Idol.</hi>
                     </q> And this be ſpoken to bid you beware of the world, if with full purpoſe of heart ye would worke for the Lord, or have a thought of joyneing with Gods people, or of their joyning with you, ye will breake the ſtaffe of beauty, and bands quickly, and away ye will goe as <hi>Demas</hi> did, <hi>having embraced the preſent world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, Is it not becauſe ye doe not ſtand in Gods Counſell, ye doe not aske at His mouth? Therefore your Judgement is ſo miſtaken in the matters, which doe concerne the glory of His houſe, and manner of His people in all times, ſpecially thoſe, which were, as ours have been, yea are <hi>fierce,</hi> and <hi>perillous, <q>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming times.</q>
                     </hi> A godly man lookes fixedly up to His God, and then downe to His Word; he will goe as far towards <q>
                        <hi>peace with all men,</hi>
                     </q> as his light will guide him, and take <hi>Holines</hi> with him; he dare not ſtep one ſtep in the darke, for then he certainly falls into ſin; more cannot be deſired, and leſſe ye cannot doe, if you doe your Duty in great matters, and in ſmall: looke to have a word for what you doe, ſo ſhall you doe things decently and in order; elſe all will be out of order, as now they are.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">BUt this making a difference, and <hi>ſeparating between the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and the vile,</hi>
                     </q> is the ſtone of ſtumbling, and gives great offence. It doth ſo, and ſo it ever did, and ſo it will, and it muſt ſo doe; To take away this offence we ſay, firſt.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Holy <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes fully to this, we thinke, <q>
                        <hi>doe I now perſwade men, or God?</hi>
                     </q> that is, doe I endeavour to perſwade with you in the things of men, or in the things of God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt? doe I plead His cauſe, or mine owne? or doe I ſeeke to pleaſe men? would I endeare my ſelfe to you, or Him to you, and His matters, of ſo neare concernment to your pretious ſoules? This I know, and would have you to know, <q>
                        <hi>If I yet pleaſed men,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41842:30"/> I ſhould not be the ſervant of Chriſt,</hi>
                     </q> Gal. 1. 10. It is not poſſible in theſe matters, but ye muſt offend God and His little ones, or ye muſt offend men, who cannot poſſibly be pleaſed; But where, and when God is highly offended, which of theſe will ye offend? when ye can no more pleaſe both, than yecan ſerve two Maſters; you can remember who ſaid it, <q rend="margQuotes">The Lord God is a glorious Friend, and as dreadfull an enemie; Therefore He had rather offend the whole world, than Him; for what can the world doe to pleaſe, or quiet the Creature, when God is diſpleaſed? or to diſquiet, diſpleaſe, or diſcompoſe him, when God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with him? <q>
                           <hi>when He giveth quietnes, who then can cauſe</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Job 34. 29.</note> 
                           <hi>trouble? and when He hideth His face</hi>
                        </q> (ſo we may underſtand it) <hi>who then can behold him?</hi> Who can endure the hideing of Gods face? we may ſafely underſtand it too; If God hide the face of a man, that is, condemne him, paſſe ſentence of death upon him; (of which hideing, or covering the face was a ſymbol)<note place="margin">Eſth: 7. 8.</note> who can behold Him? who can ſee His face, have communion<note place="margin">Mark. 14. 65.</note> with Him, whom God hath put from Him, having <hi>ſeparated</hi> him to deſtruction?</q> It is not then to be regarded, what offends men, but what offends God. Feare we God, and deſire we of Him, That He would ſtrengthen us with <q>
                        <hi>All might, according to His glorious power,</hi>
                     </q> to <hi>walke worthy of Him unto all <q>well-pleaſing,</q>
                     </hi> being fruitfull in every good worke, and encreaſing in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God: Ye will <q>
                        <hi>need all Might</hi> to enable to <hi>all pleaſing,</hi>
                     </q> and to fence you againſt the feare of men, when ye are upon this <hi>ſeparating</hi> worke. So true is that of the wiſe man, <q>
                        <hi>The feare of</hi>
                     </q>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 29. 25.</note> 
                     <hi>a man bringeth a ſnare; but who ſo putteth his truſt in the Lord ſhall be ſafe, or ſet on high.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, Obſerve what God Commands, and buckle-up to the obedience of it, and know, ye have warrant ſufficient for this, <q>
                        <hi>Have not I commanded you? Come out from among them, and be</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 17.</note> 
                        <hi>ye ſeparate, and touch not the uncleane thing, and I will receive you.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Ye ſay this is not meant of ſeparating from a Church; we ſay ſo too;</q> And that no ſuch profeſſion of ſeparation is required from this, or that, or any Church, but onely a ſeparation from the <hi>world,</hi> eſpecially at the Lords Table The Church is that; from which the rent is; <hi>Haereſie</hi> divides from the head; <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hiſme</hi> from the body; <hi>Apoſtacie</hi> from both. <hi>Schiſme</hi> is a renting from Churches, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41842:30"/> from Saints. <hi>Separation</hi> commanded by God, and practiſed by good men is onely from the world, and that which is of the world, that they may Cement, and ſodder together, being united to Chriſt their Head, and by charity one to another: ſo this ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is not for want of Charity, but in all love, and humility to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, which makes them goe ſtooping one towards another, that they may advance one th' other Heaven-ward. The Godly cannot joyne with the world in their worſhip, for then they muſt joyne with them in their ſin; ſo they are not ſo much <q>
                        <hi>drawne from the world, as driven from the world, ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ati non fugitivi.</hi> The blame of Schiſme, ſaith <hi>Voetius,</hi>
                     </q> muſt not be upon thoſe, who forſake thoſe, that have forſaken Chriſt, and His Truth; Therefore as not the <hi>puniſhment,</hi> but the <hi>Cauſe makes the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr:</hi> ſo <hi>non<q> deceſſio, ſed</q> cauſa facit ſchiſmaticum,</hi> not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, but the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſe makes the ſchiſmaticke; he or ſhe, one, or more, that is a true<q> 
                        <hi>ſeparatiſt</hi> can ſay,</q> calling God to record up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their ſoules, <q>That love to God,</q> To their owne, and others ſoules is the cauſe of their ſeparation, not want of love to their Neighbour, which may remind you of what that Excellent Italian Divine <hi>Zanchi</hi> ſaid, ſeparating from the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">I now, ſeventy yeares old, teſtifie together with my whole family, to the Church of Chriſt to all Eternity, That I ſeparated from <hi>Rome</hi> with no other intent, but to turne againe to Communion with her, ſo ſoone as ſhe is turned to the Lord, and is become as that Church was, whoſe praiſe is in the Goſpell, <q>
                           <hi>Beloved of God, called to be His Saints,</hi>
                        </q> Rom. 1. 7. So they that are followers of God, as Deare Children, can ſay, from whom ſoever they ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate now, to them they will gladly returne anone, when they ſhall be turned to the Lord, which they pray-for without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, In the laſt place, This fellowſhip of the Saints one with another at their private meetings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hath a very ill reſentment with Godly Miniſters, and Gods people alſo; ſo we have heard, and ſo indeed we find it to be; And it ſhould be, ſurely is of a ſad reſentment to all the Godly in Chriſt Jeſus all over the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; That the practice of Chriſt with His Diſciples converſing with them alone, and apart; And the practice of all true Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in all ages to this very day, ſhould be ſpoken againſt now, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41842:31"/> and quite out of uſe; For Saints not to converſe Saints, not to hold Communion together; it is to doe moſt unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comeing Saints it is indeed to <hi>unſaint themſelves,</hi> it is to make them looke not like themſelves, ſo as any one can ſay, <q>
                        <hi>There is a Saint.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>The wicked will aſſemble together, and by their will, will not have a good man amongſt them which tells us what the truely godly Miniſters, and people have done, and ſtill doe, and muſt ſo doe, if they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll approve themſelves godly, <hi>meete often together,</hi> that they may ſpeake <hi>one to another;</hi> for each others good for <hi>their Edification;</hi> And truely, we cannot Imagine, how any God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſter can doe leſſe, but encourage it, that they ſhould ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out againſt it, is a wonder; How elſe ſhall they know the ſtate of their people? how ſhall they underſtand, how they have profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? how fitt Gueſts they are for the Lords Table? but of that before.</p>
                  <p>Surely they muſt be dealt with alone, and apart in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; A Miniſter ſhall, as we are perſwaded, find no more ready a way to diſcerne between the vile, and pretious, than by appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a private meeting place, where they may conferre one with another; The Godly ſhall find the wicked will not come at them, They hate ſuch meetings as they doe the light, but what the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hate, the Godly love. The wicked will not endure to be tryed, being all <hi>droſſe,</hi> and continuing ſuch, muſt be <hi>thruſt away; And neere, and cloſe tryalls of ſincerity,</hi> as that Excellent man ſaith,<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Owen. p.</hi> 195.</note> 
                     <hi>drive Hypocrites into Apoſtacie;</hi> But ſurely this courſe muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, Miniſters muſt call their people together, they muſt meete with them often in private, elſe how ſhall they know who are fit gheſts for the Lords Table? There, there will be, as hitherto hath been, prophane mixtures, and hatefull doings there.</p>
                  <p>We conceive nothing can be reaſonably objected againſt this, onely this is ſaid, and much ſtrucke at, much the ſame the Princes had to ſay againſt <hi>Daniel, 6. 5. Theſe private meetings are in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to an higher matter, drawing towards a more cloſe walking with God, and entring into Covenant in the ſtrength of God ſo to doe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Very true, and he that opens againſt this, ſets his mouth againſt heaven; how can a people maintaine their fellowſhip with the <q>
                        <hi>Father, and the Son,</hi> and not hold fellowſhip one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</q>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:41842:31"/> and how can they walke together as Friends, and not in Goſpell order, and by Church rule? And then why not engage in the ſtrength of God, and enter into Covenant, as to this thing, to walke humbly with their God, as under His eye, and before Him, as becometh the Goſpell, and all true Goſpellers? Worthy Mr <hi>Palmer</hi> hath ſpoke much in a little to this in the beginning of his booke, which we would commend unto the Chriſtian Reader: And here we will tell our perſwaſion before we conclude<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That ſith the Holy Scripture calls the Church of God, and Church Communion, <q>
                        <hi>Heaven;</hi>
                     </q> It is not onely a Company we ſhall live<note place="margin">Iſa. 65 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6. 22.</note> withall in heaven hereafter, But it is heaven now; And they who doe not bend towards, and breath after this Communion of Saints;<note place="margin">Revel: paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> are but baſe, and unworthy perſons; The Lord God brands them, and ſo may His people, as He doth thoſe we reade off <q>
                        <hi>Theſe</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Chron. 4 23.</note> 
                        <hi>were potters, and thoſe that dwelt among Plants, and hedges: there they dwelt with the King for his worke;</hi>
                     </q> theſe were ſome baſer ſort of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> who, when liberty was proclaimed for their returne to <hi>Jeruſalem, <q>where they might enjoy God in His true worſhip,</q>
                     </hi> choſe rather for filthy Lucre ſake, and other fleſhly advantages to ſtay in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and to ſerve among the potts. The application is eaſie; We will onely offer to their thoughts, who are ſo baſely diſpoſed, that fearefull threatning, <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <q>
                        <hi>And it ſhall be,</hi>
                     </q>
                     <note place="margin">Zach. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7.</note> 
                     <hi>that whoſoever will not come-up of all the families of the earth unto Jeruſalem, to worſhip the King the <q>Lord of Hoſts, even upon them ſhall be no raine;</q>
                     </hi> no Bleſſing. This muſt be meant, as might be cleared fully, from the 20th verſe; <q rend="margQuotes">The glorious ſtate, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Church in the time of the Goſpell, walking toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Church Communion.</q> And therefore the Lord God takes it very ill, at the hands of thoſe, to whom He hath proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a Bleſſed liberty; Yet they preferring their eaſe, and profits before it, will not come-up (for it is up the Hill) to joyne with His people therein; Therefore He threatens them, as we heard, They <hi>ſhall have no <q>Bleſſing.</q>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:41842:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the ſhutting-up of all, we crave leave, firſt to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe our ſelves to your ſelfe, and brethren of the ſame perſwaſion with you. Secondly, Then to thoſe of our owne ranke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Church Communion one with another. In the third place, we will ſet downe foure ſavoury Speeches, ſpoken, as we conceive, in anſwer to this very plea againſt ſeparation here pleaded for.</p>
               <p>But before we can have the leaſt hope, that our Counſell ſhould take, we muſt take off as we can, another Reproach we ſtand aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with, which is this; <q rend="margQuotes">That we have made mention of three men (of a contrary mind and judgement to us) with honour little enough to their perſons, and contempt more than enough to their bookes; But not anſwered any one of their Arguments, no not one;</q> To this we reply.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That we cannot make honourable mention of them, who have, to our ſeeming, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt ſuch diſhonours upon our deare Lord and Saviour, His Holy things, and people of His Holineſs, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all along in their Pamphlets moſt contrary to Scripture, to Reaſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to the judgement of all the Orthodox Miniſters, and people, that ever were or now are in the world; <hi>As if the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction from God was no terrour to them, and by reaſon of His Highneſs they could endure</hi> to be an occaſion of drawing downe that Curſe upon us, whereof we read, <hi>Levit.</hi> 7. 20. More dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow under the Goſpell than that was under the Law, becauſe Goſpell Curſes are moſt dreadfull; <hi>The ſoule that eateth of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Levit. 7. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>of peace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffrings, that pertaine unto the LORD, having his uncleanneſs upon him, even that ſoule ſhall be cut off from his people.</hi> We cannot ſpeak, (becauſe we cannot think, honourably of thoſe men, that have ſpoken ſo as they have don, pleading for the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of thoſe to the <hi>Lords Table,</hi> who have all <hi>their unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon them.</hi> And yet we have not to our knowledge vilified their perſons, or ſpoken reproachfully of them, much leſs judged them as to their preſent ſtate and beeing in Chriſt; they may be for ought we know, truely Conſcientious, and men fearing God,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41842:32"/> and ſo, that they have don, hath proceeded from ignorance and miſtake: onely this ſeemes ſtrange unto us; that whereas all three have been told their errour, and little leſs than <hi>braied</hi> for it, yet they ſhould perſiſt to bring<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in that <hi>abomination</hi> into Gods houſe, which cauſeth <hi>Deſolation.</hi> We cannot think or ſpeak honourably of them for ſo doing. And have ſo <hi>erred,</hi> though not in <hi>their hearts.</hi> And yet that ſaying may command all due conſideration; <hi>An erroneous head, and a Godly heart will not meet.</hi> Corruption in judgement being like poyſon in the ſpring. But yet this Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration ſhould be for a lamention, That the <hi>envious-one</hi> called the <hi>Devill</hi> and <hi>Satan,</hi> hath ſo mightily prevailed in theſe dayes, as to make Miniſters themſelves not a few, ſtudiouſly active in the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheiving, yea ruining their owne peoples ſoules. But</p>
               <p>Secondly; As to our not Anſwering any one of their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments we ſay, That had we as many ſpare houres as there are ſpare books in the world; and as well able for ſuch a ſervice, if it may be called ſo, as they are who are beſt able, yet we had not medled with their Arguments; and theſe are our Reaſons; for</p>
               <p>Firſt, Why ſhould we <hi>actum agere</hi> doe that we find ſo cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully, ſo learnedly and holily don to our hands; ſo Mr <hi>Hs:</hi> is anſwered is he not? And Mr <hi>Prynn's</hi> twelve Arguments, if we may call them Arguments, for <hi>Free Admiſſion of all to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, It being one of the moſt effectu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll principall meanes for <q>reall Converſion;</q>
                  </hi> are Anſwered with twenty ſet againſt them by learned <hi>Gilleſpy</hi> of pleſſed Memory, which will be replied unto and rean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, when bleſſed <hi>Juel</hi> is by any of them who are of <hi>Hardings old<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Taking way</hi> and judgement, the <hi>great Rode</hi> of the world. And for <hi>John Timſons</hi> Arguments (who knows how many?) we will ſingle but one out of the throng, whereby we may make judgement of the reſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of the Anſwers thereunto; <q rend="margQuotes">Unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate perſons, ſaith he, have an hand to take, and a mouth to eat, therefore a right to receive. <hi>This Argument,</hi> ſaith worthy Mr <hi>Collings, will prove a Monkies right to it alſo;</hi> I had thought the takeing, eating and drinking muſt be ſpirituall by faith; he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how we will prove it?</q> And in a bold confidence, that this cannot be proved, he hath argued the Caſe afreſh this laſt yeare, againſt two of his <hi>good Maſters.</hi> And now we have Cauſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, he will be anſwered with <hi>ſilence,</hi> theſe worthy men Mr <hi>Hs:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41842:33"/> Sanders,</hi> and M <hi>John Collings</hi> having, as we conceive, a command from their God, <hi>Anſwer him not;</hi> his <hi>errour,</hi> which ſome may call <hi>folly</hi> will not, by that meanes, depart from him. They will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him to God, and <hi>Word of His Grace,</hi> which is able to doe that which all the ableſt men in the world are not able to doe, <hi>make his folly depart from him.</hi> In the next place becauſe;</p>
               <p>Secondlly, To make Anſwer was no part of our undertaking, but to give-in our perſwaſion in ſome matters before ſpecified in their proper place to a neighbour Miniſter calling us to an account about them; and in ſpeciall about <hi>free Admiſſion of all to all Church Communions.</hi> This we have don according to <hi>our Meaſure,</hi> looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the foundation upon which their whole building ſtands, and taking away that rotten pillar, which upholds it which is this; <q rend="margQuotes">That being baptized into a Church, they are all holy every one, and <hi>eo nomine,</hi> all have a right to all Church Communions, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they be <hi>children in yeares, fooles or mad men.</hi>
                  </q> This is the very <hi>ſubſtratum</hi> or <hi>underbearer,</hi> upon which their building ſtands, And whereby a <hi>great multitude which no man can number,</hi> being <hi>as the ſand of the Sea,</hi> are built up as high as Heaven, and, having no other <hi>ſtay</hi> to <hi>leane to</hi> muſt be caſt down to the lowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moſt Hell: To looſen this <hi>ſandy</hi> foundation, and to throw down this rotten building, or dawbed <hi>wall,</hi> before the great <hi>haileſtones fall,</hi> and <hi>a ſtormie wind rents it,</hi> was a great part of our undertaking; that we might caſt a flood, if poſſible, and utterly drown the <hi>fooles para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe,</hi> or lay our batteriers to his <hi>Caſtle</hi> he <hi>hath</hi> (by your good help, the Maſter-builder) <hi>built in the Aire;</hi> his <hi>ſtrong Confidence,</hi> we meane, <hi>that being borne and baptized in a Church,</hi> he is a priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged man to <hi>abide in Gods Tabernacle</hi> here below, and to dwell in <hi>His Holy Hill</hi> for ever and ever above in the higheſt Heaven Had we the Confidence of one man, we would ſpeak as he doth; <q rend="margQuotes">for ſhame therefore diſclaime this abſurd irreligious <hi>paradox</hi>' for which there is not the leaſt ſhadow of Scripture or ſolid rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</q> A glorious Saint put a ſhort Queſtion, and a ſhorter Anſwer thereunto, we will ſet it down, and ſo an end of this matter; <hi>What brings men to hell in the Church? falſe Confidence,</hi> ſaith he, <q rend="margQuotes">They beare themſelves up as high as heaven, becauſe they were borne and baptized in a Church; they muſt be thrown-down as low as Hell, If they have no other <hi>leane-to,</hi> to beare them up.</q> Having <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:41842:33"/> with ſorrowes. We will commend to your Reading, as we ſaid,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>otam di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> onem quàm lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>è pateat Eccleſie ſingulls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Chriſti &amp; Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae proſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, pro ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ate veifrâ veni e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es adjuvando, dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mientes excitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>; nihil cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantes &amp; igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes accerſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> Jun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and beſt obſervation, and the Lord ſett it home unto you* <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62. 10. as our Engliſh, 12, as <hi>Junius</hi> devides the Chapter, with his notes upon it; and ſo we commend you to God, and the worke of His Grace with you.</p>
               <p>To your ſelfe Sir, who were the occaſion of all, ſo this we would ſpeake as <hi>Hierom</hi> to <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Si Culpa eſt reſpondiſſe, quaſo ut patienter audias, multò major eſt provocaſſe; ſed faceſſant iſtiuſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di querimoniae, ſit inter nos pura Germanitas, &amp; deinceps non que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionum, ſed charitatis ad nos ſcripta mittamus.</hi>
                  </q> But then you muſt come cleare off from that horrid opinion ſo often mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>That the Receiving the Lords Supper</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>6</label> Secondly, Now to our ſelves, and thoſe of the ſame ranke with us, endeavouring after the ſame thing, <hi>purity of Doctrine,</hi> of <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, and life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, Let us not trouble our ſelves with controverted points; True it is, in ſome Caſes, <hi>Expoſitorum diverſitas excitat attentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> Diverſitie of opinions, make the hearer more attent. But this is never where the Text is plaine; or if he be more attent he will be more unreſolved. It is as true alſo, That Truth getts ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by a neceſſary conflict of arguments, but this is among the Learned in the Schooles; and when the Caſe admitts of ſome doubts; ſeldome or never among thoſe of our ranke; And where the Caſe is cleare and reſolved. Diſputes among ſuch, and in ſuch caſes, the more amuzes them, putting them into Doubts, where they ſhould make none; None at all; None at all, as we conceive and have proved, whether all are to be admitted to the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? Whether <hi>Chriſtmas-day,</hi> as we call it, with the like, of the ſame ſtamp, or inſtitution, is to be kept <hi>holy?</hi> And being reſolved at that point, as you are, in the Negative, then, whether a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſt ought not contend with the obſervers of that <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then-Feaſt;</hi> as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did with the Nobles prophaning the <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> at leaſt by conniving at thoſe, who did. 13. 17. we take it, that ſuch cleared Truths as theſe and thoſe relating to <hi>formes of prayer,</hi> are not to be put to queſtion, or if they be, we are not, as we conceive, to be carefull to anſwer in theſe matters; we are not to <hi>deliberate</hi> upon them. They that will put theſe things to queſtion, may feare to be delivered-up into a minde voyde of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41842:34"/> judgement. And they that are reſolved in theſe points, and would reſolve the gaine-ſayers; Let them looke into their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. For what hope have they, of our ranke, to prevaile with thoſe, who have withſtood the Reſolves from Gods word by the mouth of Gods faithfull Miniſters? They that contend for theſe matters, are not <hi>weake ones,</hi> but vaine and ſuperſtitious perſons, built-up high in their fleſhly confidences, ſo as your words can move with them, no more, than can a blaſt of winde move a tower of braſſe, or the waves a rocke. In a word; Let not us diſpute Gods right, but give it Him; nor the lawes of His houſe, but give our obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation unto them; nor the way of His people, but walke we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and with ſo right a foote in deſire and endeavour, that we may put a beauty upon the way, and ſo adorne it, that we may draw others to it, to walke together with us as Friends in it, having concluded within themſelves, making obſervation by our walke; <hi>This is the way of Holineſſe; for ſee how Holily they walke, who are walkers in it;</hi> Onely take this with it more, ſuſpect that at the leaſt, to be a <hi>curſed liberty</hi> the worldly Church contends for; and reckon upon that to be <hi>the Holy way,</hi> they would ſtand up againſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting and blaſpheming.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the ſecond place. Let us pray God make us Learned to the Kingdome of God; That we may humble all our knowledge to the obedience of Faith. God grant to all his people the Spirit of wiſedome and underſtanding, That they may be able to diſcerne the Spirits, whether they are of God, or no. That they may take heed of falſe Prophets, and give eare to the voyce of the Prince of Paſtors, and fly the voyce of ſtrangers, and beware of blinde Guides that ſo often have deceived them. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">§ </seg>7</label> Thirdly, In the laſt place, We will ſett downe thoſe foure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury Speeches, we before made mention of. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Chillingworth</hi> ſpeakes firſt, what the goodneſſe of the man was, we know not, but this ſpeech is very good, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">If I did not finde in my ſelfe a love and deſire of all profitable Truth; if I did not put away idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and earthly affection, and to ſearch to the bottome of my opinions in reference to Divine matters, being prepared in my mind to follow God, and Him onely, which way ſoever He ſhall leade me; If I did not hope, that I either doe, or endeavour theſe things; Certainly I ſhould have (little comfort in my
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41842:34"/> ſeparation from the world at preſent and) little hope of obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſalvation hereafter;</q> There is the firſt ſpeech.</p>
               <p>Mr <hi>H: Sanders</hi> ſpeech is next: <q rend="margQuotes">The power of godlines is firſt<note place="margin">Pag. 175.</note> to be heeded; if we be nothing within; no great matter, though we ſit at the right, or the left hand of Chriſts outward King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; let us contend principally to be members of Chriſt, to be of the inviſible Church, imbodied in the Church of the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne; here we cannot eaſily be too carefull or too curious. But as to externall fellowſhip, though the mind of Chriſt in this alſo be to be ſought, and followed; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et ſo much earneſtneſſe, and confidence needs not, as in the other, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſſe men take care how to live, 'tis not much matter, how they worſhip.</hi> Thou maiſt be, (this we take to our ſelves, as chearefully, and thankfully, as this good man ſpake it to himſelfe, and his good people hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily) in a purer Church than another, and yet be the impurer, and vainer ſoule of the two; It is better to ſee a mans Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, commending his way, than to ſee men beholding to their way for their eſteeme.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Mr <hi>Ant: Palmers</hi> words follow; <q rend="margQuotes">An holy fellowſhip with<note place="margin">Sermon upon <hi>Math:</hi> 8. 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, <hi>p.</hi> 85.</note> ſuch as are Godly, by frequent Conference; communicating their experiences of God in a more holy Church-fellowſhip than the mixt Congregations are yet reduced into, will abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly quicken and ſtrengthen faith, and every gift and grace of beleevers; and make much for the retaining and encreaſe of comfort.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Dr <hi>Owens</hi> words follow, and therewith we will cloſe all; <q rend="margQuotes">You<note place="margin">On <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17. 24. <hi>p.</hi> 32.</note> that doe enjoy Holy Ordinances, Labour to have holy hearts anſwerable thereunto: you have heavenly inſtitutions, labour to have heavenly Converſations; if we be like the world in our walking, it is no great matter, if we be like the world in our worſhip: it is ſad walking contrary to God in His owne Paths; ſhew-out the power, and efficacie of all Goſpell Inſtitutions in a frame of Spirit, courſe of life, and equability of ſpirituall tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per all your dayes. Keepe up the power of private worſhip, both perſonall, and family. I have ſeene many good Lawes for the Sabbath, and hope I ſhall ſee ſome good examples: <hi>Looke what the roots are in the family, ſuch will the fruit be, in the Church, and Common-wealth: if your ſpirits are not well manured</hi>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:41842:35"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:41842:35"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:41842:36"/> 
                     <hi>there, you will be utterly barren elſewhere: that is done moſt cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, which is done within dores.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This being ſet home by the Spirit of holineſſe, will keepe our foote cloſe-up to <hi>wiſedomes</hi> wayes, which are pleaſantnes, and all her paths peace, and tends to that Bleſſed End, that hath no End, <hi>Eternall life.</hi> Excellent <hi>Bradfords</hi> good Counſell, and prayer ſhall put a cloſe to all.</p>
               <p>Moleſt not the good Spirit of God, which is given you, as a gage of Eternall Redemption, a Counſellour, and Maſter to lead you into all truth; which good Spirit, I beſeech the Father of mercies to give unto us all, for His Deare Sonnes ſake, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, our Lord; To whom I Commend you all, and to the word of His grace, which is able to helpe you all, that beleeve it, follow it, and ſerve God, thereafter.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:41842:36"/>
            <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>THe Author humbly craves leave [after he hath mentioned onely (1) <hi>Auguſtines</hi> ſhort Apologie for his long work, which will fit the Author very well ſpeaking that in ſeaven Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, which might have been ſpoken, as one ſpake, in ſo many pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, if not in ſo many lines; <hi>That he much diſliked, if not deteſted,</hi> as his friend <hi>Nebridius</hi> did, <hi>a ſhort anſwer to a great queſtion, and would not that any ſhould expect the like from him, for then he would manifeſt his indignation againſt it.</hi> And (2) what <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> ſpake of old to the old Heathen; <hi>Theſe things we offer to your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration; If they ſeeme agreeable, to true Reaſon, and Scripture Truth, accept, and put an account upon them: If they ſeeme toyes, as ſuch contemne them; but doe not hoſtilely perſecute them.</hi> And (3) he would humbly offer to Conſideration what Learned Mr <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Jenkin</hi> hath for the clearing the two cheife <hi>Heads</hi> of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie here debated-on; <hi>Admiſſion of all Infants to Baptiſm: And grown perſons to the Lords Table</hi> In his expoſition upon <hi>Jude,</hi> ſecond part, <hi>pag.</hi> 274, 275, 276, 277, 278.] After theſe three things, as the Author was ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he humbly craves leave, he may cloſe his booke, with the very words, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> cloſeth his of the <hi>City of God.</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Videor mihi</hi> &amp;c. I thinke with my ſelfe, I have, by the ſupply of His Spirit, done my Dutie, and diſcharged the Debt, I ſaw my ſelfe bound to pay to my Lord; to His houſe and His people. Now they that thinke I have ſaid too little, they alſo that thinke I have ſaid too much, Let both th' one and the other pardon me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And they that thinke I have ſaid e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, Let them give the praiſe not to me (I wholy diſclaime it) but to their's and my Lord God with me. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And Obſerving <hi>Lod<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Vives</hi> in his Commentary, ſpeaking as properly; take his words too<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">If I have ſpoken that which plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, let the Reader thanke God in my behalfe; if any thing that diſpleaſeth, let him pardon it for the Lord God's ſake. And for that which is well ſpoken, let him pardon that which may be ill
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41842:37"/> ſpoken, though never ſo well meant.</q> The following words doe not fit this work, nor this place, for the Author cannot expect that from the Readers, though never ſo Curteous, which, having neither time nor oportunity, he could not poſſibly doe himſelfe; he meanes the Correcting the miſtakes here, which muſt be many, when th' Author could at no time be adviſed with. And to point to one or two miſtaks where the ſenſe may be miſtaken by it, were there leyſure for it, would little advantage the Reader, for <hi>quid exempta juvat—de pluribus vua;</hi> The Reader readily grants that favour, he himſelfe may crave.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>An Advertiſement of certaine Bookes ſold by <hi>Henry Cripps</hi> in <hi>Popes-head-Alley.</hi> With a ſhort Apologie of the Author premiſed, why he is willing ſuch publick notice ſhould be given thereof.</head>
            <p>TRUTH, hath ſaid it; <hi>How can ye beleeve, which receive ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour one of another, and ſeeke not the honour that cometh from God onely.</hi> Theſe words gave ſome check or diſcouragement at the firſt; but after due conſideration, encouragement rather; for if this be the Aime and End of publiſhing to the world theſe Books, <hi>the ſeeking honour of men;</hi> or, <hi>loving the praiſe of men, more than the praiſe of God</hi> (If by theſe meanes it might be gained) Then let the Lord God blaſt the work and the work-man; Make him and it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as the untimely fruit, which withereth before the Sunne. But if the work-man in all this, hath, through Grace, Holy Aimes and pure ends; The Glory of God, and the good of his Neighbour, in rendring the doctrine hereafter mentioned (and the bare-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning thereof is enough to render it an) abomination through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the land, which cauſeth deſolation there; Then let him and his work be bleſſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And <hi>let his God remember him concerning this alſo, and ſpare him according to the greatneſſe of His mercy.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:41842:37"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE LORDS TABLE ought not to be ſpread like that in an Inne for all commers,</hi> publiſhed that it might prove an <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote</hi> againſt the ſpreading infection of that poyſonfull doctrine, <hi>That all are to be admitted to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, It being one of the moſt effectuall principall meanes for reall Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> (ſaith one next mentioned, the other ſay the ſame thing, though not in the ſame words) held-out in three <hi>pernicious Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, which eat as doth a Canker;</hi> The one publiſhed by M<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Prynne</hi> ſome yeares ſince called <hi>A vindication of foure ſerious Queſtions;</hi> Th' other by Mr <hi>Humpheryes,</hi> notorious all over the Nation The third by <hi>John Timſon</hi> this laſt yeare, after learned M <hi>Joh: Collings</hi> would have <hi>forbad</hi> th' errour of the man, which ſome may call his <hi>folly,</hi> or <hi>madnes,</hi> ſpeaking in moſt pages of his ſaid Pamphlet, as a man that had depoſed reaſon, and ſo could ſpeake croſs to ſacred Scripture, right reaſon, and the judgement of all the orthodox Miniſters and people, that ever were, or now are in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>FO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R GRAND ENQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IRIES,</hi> wherein the foundation, whereon that bloody and damnable Doctrine aforeſaid, beareth, is looſened, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">That all perſons baptized into a Church, are all holy, and <hi>eo nomine,</hi> have a right to all Church-Communions, they and their children, how abominable ſoever they are, ſo be they are not ſuſpended from, not excommunicated out of the Church, nor are children in yeares, fooles, or mad men.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LAW-POWER,</hi> wherein we may ſee, The <hi>Way of Holineſſe</hi> paved forth before us, and troden-in by all thoſe Miniſters and people, who have felt the law of their Relation written in their hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A TREATISE OF PRAYEY,</hi> wherein two Queſtions are reſolved touching <hi>formes of prayer,</hi> both in the Negative, <hi>That they are not good for the evill, nor of any uſe for the good to teach them to pray.</hi> And ſix touching the <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> all in the Negative, two onely are ſpecified here (1) That the intendment of our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> was not that His Diſciples then or now ſhould pray in thoſe very words. (2) Nor is the repeating that prayer in the pulpit, the <hi>Teſſera</hi> of a Godly Miniſter, becauſe the <hi>hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:41842:38"/> that prayer after the manner, may ſhew the man not ſo ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as ridiculous in praying.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>INFANT BAPTISM is not the priviledge of all Infants up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bare account onely of their parents Baptiſm,</hi> publiſhed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the <hi>FO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R ENQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IRIES</hi> to prevent the evill may be taken-in from ſome unſcripturall paſſages not <hi>becomming ſound doctrine,</hi> which the Reader may find in a <hi>Dialogue concerning the practicall uſe of Infant Baptiſm</hi> towards the end of the ſame, compoſed by a learned Divine, and as is meet to think, orthodox, pious, and Godly in other points, though in his zeal at this point, it is conceived, he hath erred with his pen, not taking the Word of God for the <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CHRISMAS DAY no Holy Day,</hi> publiſhed to prevent thoſe heathen and raunting practiſes; ſuperſtitious cuſtomes, Abominable prophaneſſes in faſhion at that time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A MINISTERS D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TY,</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">to Declare againſt all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and practiſes contrary to ſound Doctrine, and practiſe of Chriſt Himſelf, and all thoſe He <hi>accounts faithfull</hi> putting them into the Miniſtery.</q> Wherein it is proved alſo, That if a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter will live peaceable and quiet among ſinners, he muſt ſuffer them to be at peace and quiet with their ſinnes, <hi>peaceableneſſe of ſinners being nothing elſe, but impiety not oppoſed, in themſelves, or by others; for, who ever is not oppoſed by the ſtreame, goeth with it;</hi> and altogether, who will to the <hi>Lords-Table.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH-COVENANT,</hi> lawfull and needfull to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into by all, that intend to walk in Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fellowſhip accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Goſpel order.</p>
            <p>The Authors Name is annexed to th' Epiſtle before theſe Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes; and the Reaſons of making them ſo publick are given on the back-ſide of the generall Title page.</p>
            <div type="binding_instructions">
               <head>Direction to the Binder.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GEnerall Title; Appeal; Conference; Infant Baptiſm; Lords Table; Chriſtmas; Formes of prayer; Miniſters duty; four Grand Enquiries; Law-power; Covenant;</hi> the <hi>Account</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions</hi> may be ſtitched alone. If altogether then <hi>Account</hi> before the <hi>Appeal,</hi> and <hi>Exceptions</hi> after <hi>Infant Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41842:38"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
